<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain selected odes of Horace, Englished; and their arguments annexed. VVith poems (antient and modern) of divers subiects, translated. Whereunto are added, both in Latin and English, sundry new epigrammes. Anagramms. Epitaphes</title>
            <title>Carmina. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Horace.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104225</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839964</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839964</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4430</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03671)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4430)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1177:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain selected odes of Horace, Englished; and their arguments annexed. VVith poems (antient and modern) of divers subiects, translated. Whereunto are added, both in Latin and English, sundry new epigrammes. Anagramms. Epitaphes</title>
                  <title>Carmina. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Horace.</author>
                  <author>Ashmore, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H[umphrey] L[ownes] for Richard Moore; and are to be solde at his shop in Saint Dunstans Church-yard, in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated and with additional verse by John Ashmore.</note>
                  <note>The words "epigrammes. Anagramms. Epitaphes." are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "B" between two woodcut ornaments.</note>
                  <note>"Epigrammes, epitaphes, anagrammes, and other poems of diuers subiects" has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Epigrams, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4430:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4430:1"/>
            <p>CERTAIN SELECTED ODES OF HORACE, ENGLISH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and their Arguments <hi>annexed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Poems (Antient and Modern) of divers Subiects, Tranſlated.</p>
            <p>Whereunto are added, both in Latin and <hi>Engliſh, ſundry new</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>EPIGRAMMES.</item>
               <item>ANAGRAMMS.</item>
               <item>EPITAPHES.</item>
            </list>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device? (not indexed in McKerrow) or decoration</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Richard Moore;</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop in Saint <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church-yard, in Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4430:2"/>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:4430:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Rectangular illustration with center circle containing a wheat sheaf supported by two animals, around which are the words: "Cor unum via una" (description from EEBO catalogue record of Tract Supplement / E4:1[52a] which consists entirely of this same device)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>RVERENDISSIMO IN CHRISTO PATRI ET DOMINO, D. TOBIAE, Archiepiſcopo <hi>Eboracenſi, Angl. Primati &amp; Metropolitano digniſsimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <label>ANAGR.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>TωBIAS MATHEVS.</item>
                     <item>I HOMO SAT BEATVS.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <lg>
               <head>EPIGR. de Eodem.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ipſe beatus homo es, coeleſtia dona beatum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si faciant.</hi> I: SAT <hi>nempe</hi> BEATVS HOMO <hi>es.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <list>
               <label>Aliud.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>TωBIAS MATHEIVS.</item>
                     <item>IEHOVA SIT MI SABOT.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <lg>
               <head>Epigram.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tranquillâ pacis mea mens ſic ſede locata,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>MI <hi>terrae ſaturo,</hi> SIT <hi>que</hi> IEHOVA SABOT.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg xml:lang="eng">
               <head>Angl.</head>
               <l>My Soule, SIT in the ſeat of Safety, bleſt:</l>
               <l>IEHOVA is MI SABOT, my ſweet Reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <pb facs="tcp:4430:3"/>
               <head>Ad Eundem.</head>
               <l>SI tibi (cui reſerant ſacrae ſua clauſtra Camoenae,</l>
               <l>Cuius &amp; à labijs Attica mella fluunt)</l>
               <l>Haec non diſpliceant Venuſini carmina vatis,</l>
               <l>Strididulae (ut potui) mî modulata lyrae,</l>
               <l>Sed vultus crepta tui ſplendore tenebris,</l>
               <l>Incipiant coelo liberiore frui;</l>
               <l>Non ronchos metuam, non vani ſcommata vulgi,</l>
               <l>Cenſores tetricos, grammaticáſve Tribus.</l>
               <l>Solus eris contra haec <hi>Aiacis</hi> ſpicula ſcutum;</l>
               <l>Dulce &amp; praeſidium Tu mihi ſolus eris.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Angl.</head>
               <l>IF Thee, the Muſes ſacred Rites that knowes,</l>
               <l>And from whoſe Lips pure Attick Hony flowes,</l>
               <l>Theſe Lyrick Poet's Songs doo not diſpleaſe,</l>
               <l>Tun'd (as I could) to my Pipe's homely Laies,</l>
               <l>But (doom'd to darknes) by thy gracefull Sight</l>
               <l>Bee brought abroad, to ſee the gladſome Light;</l>
               <l>No gleering Scorns I'll fear, nor ſpitefull Gibes,</l>
               <l>Nor crabbed Criticks, nor Grammarian Tribes.</l>
               <l>Thou, thou alone, 'gainſt all theſe Darts ſhalt bee</l>
               <l>An <hi>Aiax</hi>-Shield, and ſweet Defence to mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Amplitudini tuae, omni obſervantiâ devotus, IOH: ASHMORE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:4430:3"/>
            <head>To my Friend, the Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TO praiſe Thee, is a Labour to no end;</l>
               <l>Since thoſe, that read Thee, cannot but Commend.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Envie</hi> read, and <hi>Envie</hi> will becom</l>
               <l>A <hi>Convert;</hi> or, at leaſt, ſhee will be dum.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="encomium">
            <head>
               <hi>Ad Amicum ſuum,</hi> Ioh. Aſhmore.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LAus in laudato, non in laudante, Poëta est:</l>
               <l>Laus meritum ſequitur, corpus ut umbra ſuum.</l>
               <l>Extollam licèt ergo tuos ad ſydera Verſus</l>
               <l>Laudibus, extollent te tua Metra magis.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ioh. Owen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>In harum Eligantiſs. Odarum Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlationem, <hi>Hexaſtichon.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>EN,</hi> Flaccus <hi>rediviuus adeſt; nimiumque negatâ</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anglica dulce melos protulit arte lyra.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Flaccus <hi>adest: Eadem mens eſt, &amp; carminis idem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Senſus: forma eadem eſt, ingenij que genus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Flaccus <hi>eris totus, ſi qui aſpiraverit orſis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sit tibi</hi> Mecaenas <hi>(docte Poëta) tuis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Samuel Pullein.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:4430:4"/>
            <head>To the ingenious Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MVch have I read: but, never could I finde</l>
               <l>A Poëm that ſo well did pleaſe my Minde,</l>
               <l>As thy ſweet Numbers. It is hard to tell,</l>
               <l>The Matter, or the Manner, which excell.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Work</hi> of Thine, with ſuch Perfection fram'd,</l>
               <l>So Scholler-like, may Others make aſham'd</l>
               <l>(When they reflect upon thy Straines their ſight)</l>
               <l>To publiſh their Compoſures to the Light.</l>
               <l>Let no brow-bended envious Carper ſay,</l>
               <l>That my Affection made my Iudgement ſtray.</l>
               <l>Such Statelineſs doth in thy Poëms dwell,</l>
               <l>That what thou writ'ſt but few can Parallel.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Cordin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <l>GRac't by the Muſes, Poët moſt expert,</l>
            <lg>
               <l>My Praiſes cannot equall thy Deſert.</l>
               <l>My raviſht Soule thy rare Straines doth admire,</l>
               <l>And thy ſweet Muſes high aſpiring fire.</l>
               <l>Come Poëts; and his temples Crown with <hi>Bayes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not many have, or can write better Layes.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4430:4"/>
                  <head>CERTAIN SELEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED ODES OF HORACE TRANSLATED.</head>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Ad Mecaenatem. Lib. 1. Ode prima.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>That many a way, moſt men aſſay</l>
                           <l>Their heads up high to raiſe:</l>
                           <l>Which he neglects, and moſt affects</l>
                           <l>A Lyrick Poets praiſe.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <head>The Engliſh anſwereth the Latine, in Lines and ſyllables.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>MEcaenas,</hi> of the race of Kings thy grandſires, bred,</l>
                        <l>O thou my chief ſupport, &amp; garland of my head;</l>
                        <l>Some with Olympian duſt beſmeard delight to ride</l>
                        <l>In Chariots, and the burning wheeles with skill to guide</l>
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4430:5"/>
                        <l>Faſt by the mark, whom victory and palms of praiſe,</l>
                        <l>With ſhouts unto the gods, Lords of the earth, doth raiſe.</l>
                        <l>This man's puft up, if fickle Romans doe agree</l>
                        <l>To reare him up with ſtiles of three fold dignitie.</l>
                        <l>If he in Garners ſafely have laid up in ſtore</l>
                        <l>His corne from <hi>Affrick</hi> brought, he careth for no more.</l>
                        <l>He that in peace at home delights his Land to till,</l>
                        <l>On no condition unto him propoſed, will</l>
                        <l>Turne Mariner, and feare-full with a <hi>Cyprian</hi> plank</l>
                        <l>Cut out a way through hils and dales of billowes rank.</l>
                        <l>The Marchant, fearing windes that in th' <hi>Icarian</hi> Seas</l>
                        <l>Doe wraſtle in great rage, the countrey life doth praiſe,</l>
                        <l>And their town fields: Then ſtraight his ſhake-ſhip doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair,</l>
                        <l>Vntaught the ſcorn-full wrongs of poverty to bear.</l>
                        <l>In froathing boawles of generous wine he healths doth drink,</l>
                        <l>And buſies not his brain, of State affaires to think;</l>
                        <l>But careleſs under th' Arbute ſhade ſometime he lies,</l>
                        <l>Somtime by th' holy well where bubbling waters riſe.</l>
                        <l>In camps entrencht<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; trumpets ſound ſom men delight,</l>
                        <l>And in ſtiff ſhocks of bloody wars that matrons fright.</l>
                        <l>The huntſman ſtayes ith' cold with hazard of his life,</l>
                        <l>Vnmindfull how hee left his young and tender wife;</l>
                        <l>Whether his truſtie Dogges purſue the fleeing Deer,</l>
                        <l>Or the revenge-full Boars the toyles aſunder teare.</l>
                        <l>The Ivie wreathes, rewards that learned for-heads get,</l>
                        <l>Me canoniz'd among the higheſt gods will ſet.</l>
                        <l>The pleaſant groves, the light-foot Nymphs, and Satyrs dance,</l>
                        <l>Shall me above the vulgar ſort of men advance,</l>
                        <l>If <hi>Euterpe</hi> my pipes ſtop not, nor the ſweet Muſe</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Polymnia</hi> my Lesbian Harp to tune refuſe.</l>
                        <l>But if that thou among the Lyrick Poets place me,</l>
                        <l>Not heaven it ſelf can then with more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment grace me.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4430:5"/>
                     <head>Ad Licinium. Lib. 2. Ode 10.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>Thoſe that deſire ſoone to aſpire</l>
                           <l>To happineſſe of life,</l>
                           <l>By th' golden meane, the ſame muſt gain,</l>
                           <l>Which most is freed from ſtrife.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THou ſhalt <hi>Licinius</hi> better live, if ſtill</l>
                        <l>Thy Bark thou doe not force into the Deep;</l>
                        <l>Or, ore-much fearing leſt rough windes ſhould fill</l>
                        <l>Thy ſailes, too neer the crooked ſhore do creep.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He that regards and loues the golden meane,</l>
                        <l>Is not with ſmoak of his poore houſe blear-ey'd:</l>
                        <l>And, well advis'd, he blends not with the traine</l>
                        <l>Of mighty Princes that are moſt envy'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Oft-times, the windes do toſs the Cedars tall:</l>
                        <l>And ſtately Towers up-reard into the ayre,</l>
                        <l>With greater danger to the earth do fall:</l>
                        <l>And thunder-bolts the higheſt hils doe teare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In all diſtreſs, a well inſtructed minde</l>
                        <l>Hope intertaines: And feares, when fortune ſmiles,</l>
                        <l>That ſuddenly ſhee'll turne and prove unkinde.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ioue</hi> black fac't winters brings and them exiles.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4430:6"/>
                        <l>If now wiſht-for ſucceſs do thee refuſe,</l>
                        <l>Think not that ſtill it will continue ſo:</l>
                        <l>Sometime <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Harp the drooping Muſe</l>
                        <l>Strikes up; Nor bends he ſtill his angry bowe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If clowds of hard mishap ore-caſt thy day,</l>
                        <l>With beames of thy great courage them expell:</l>
                        <l>And when thy Ship doth dance upon the Sea,</l>
                        <l>Led down the ſailes with too proud windes that ſwell.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Ad Lydiam. Lib. 1. Ode 13.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>It much him mooves, that <hi>Lydia</hi> loues</l>
                           <l>His Rivall: And their life</l>
                           <l>He doth commend, whoſe loue toth' end</l>
                           <l>Continueth without ſtrife.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHen <hi>Lydia</hi> thou of <hi>Telephus</hi> doſt tell,</l>
                        <l>His roſie neck and plyant armes doſt praiſe,</l>
                        <l>My liver then (alas!) begins to ſwell,</l>
                        <l>Enrag'd with wrath which nothing can appeaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My colour, changing oft, doth plainely ſhew</l>
                        <l>How my perplexed minde is plung'd in woe:</l>
                        <l>And tears, by ſtealth from watry eyes that flowe,</l>
                        <l>Can nothing quench loves fire that ſtill doth growe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4430:6"/>
                        <l>I vexed am, whether iarre-breeding wine</l>
                        <l>Caus'd roaring Boyes to wrong thy ſhoulders faire;</l>
                        <l>Or the Luſt-raging Lad, thoſe lips of thine</l>
                        <l>The wanton marke caus'd of his tooth to beare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Beleeve me, he will never conſtant prove,</l>
                        <l>That rudely wrongs ſweet kiſſes in ſuch ſort;</l>
                        <l>Thoſe kiſſes, which the Goddeſs faire of loue</l>
                        <l>Graceth with the fift part of her beſt ſport.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thrice happy, and more happy, are they ſure,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe mutuall love ſo baniſheth all ſtrife,</l>
                        <l>That pure and conſtant it doth ſtill endure</l>
                        <l>Till Fates cut off their well-ſpun thread of life.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Ad Groſphum. Lib. 2. Ode 16.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>No outward thing thee well can bring</l>
                           <l>Vnto a quiet minde.</l>
                           <l>Within it is, that brings this bliſs:</l>
                           <l>There helpe we beſt may finde.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THe Marchant toyl'd in the <hi>Egëan</hi> Sea,</l>
                        <l>When <hi>Phoebe</hi>'s face is vail'd with a dark cloud,</l>
                        <l>And the known ſtars from ſight are fled away,</l>
                        <l>For eaſe unto the gods doth cry aloud.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4430:7"/>
                        <l>For Eaſe, the <hi>Thracians</hi> (terrible in warre)</l>
                        <l>For Eaſe, the <hi>Medes</hi> (with comely quivers bold)</l>
                        <l>O <hi>Groſphus,</hi> to the gods ſtill ſuters are,</l>
                        <l>Bought with no gems, with purple, or with gold.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No treaſure, neither Sergeant can arreſt</l>
                        <l>The wretched hurly-burlies of the minde,</l>
                        <l>And cares with reſt-leſs wings that beat the breaſt,</l>
                        <l>And in faire-fretted roofes ſtill harbour finde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He lives well with a little, that doth keep</l>
                        <l>His late Sires table furniſht with meane fare;</l>
                        <l>That is not robd of reſt, nor ſcar'd from ſleep</l>
                        <l>With hide-bound Avarice, or heart-ſcorching Care.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Why doe we, ſhort-liv'd things, on tentars ſet</l>
                        <l>Our greedy thoughts with vaine deſire of pelf?</l>
                        <l>In climats furtheſt off, What would we get?</l>
                        <l>Who, from his Countrey exil'd, flees from himſelfe?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Care, vice-borne, climbs into the braſs-ſtemd ſhips:</l>
                        <l>In warlike troupes her ſelfe ſhe ſlily ſhrowds:</l>
                        <l>Swifter then Stags, ſwifter then windes ſhe skips,</l>
                        <l>That do diſperſe, and drive away the clowds.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Be Ioviall while time ſerves (Time will not ſtay.)</l>
                        <l>Hate curiouſly t' enquire what will betide:</l>
                        <l>Sowr diſcontentments with ſweet mirth allay.</l>
                        <l>Entirely good, nothing doth ſtill abide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Vntimely death did ſtout <hi>Achilles</hi> ſlay:</l>
                        <l>Old age <hi>Tithonus</hi> did Epitomize:</l>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:4430:7"/>
                        <l>And my birth-ſtar perhaps grants me a day</l>
                        <l>To date my life; which thine to thee denies.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Faire flocks of ſheep, fat heards of cattell low</l>
                        <l>About thee, and thy luſtfull Mare with pride</l>
                        <l>Neighs out, now for the Chariot fit: and thou</l>
                        <l>Wearſt purple, twice in <hi>Tyrian</hi> liquors dy'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Deſt'nie, ne'r deceiv'd, on me beſtowes</l>
                        <l>A little ground, and veine of Poëſie</l>
                        <l>Which from the pleaſant Greekiſh fountains flowes,</l>
                        <l>And th' un-taught Vulgar wils me to defie.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>In ambitioſum quenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; avaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Li. 2. Od. 18</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>That hee's content with his ſmall rent;</l>
                           <l>When richer ſtill doe crave,</l>
                           <l>And for more look by hook or crook</l>
                           <l>Though one foot in the grave.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>NO Ivory ſeeling, nor roofe adorned</l>
                        <l>With light-out-ſtreaming gold, in my houſe ſhineth:</l>
                        <l>No beames from <hi>Hymet</hi> preſs pillars formed</l>
                        <l>Where the sky-touching hill <hi>Affrick</hi> confineth.</l>
                        <l>No wealth by ill meanes doe I win,</l>
                        <l>Nor for mee clyents purple ſpin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4430:8"/>
                        <l>But of truſt and wit ſome ſtore have I:</l>
                        <l>To me but poor, come men rais'd high by fortune:</l>
                        <l>More of the Gods themſelves ne'r crave I,</l>
                        <l>Nor greater things of my great friend importune:</l>
                        <l>I wiſh not for more land or rent.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sabine</hi> alone yeelds me content.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>One day another day expelleth,</l>
                        <l>New-moons ſoon die: Thou marble-trimmers hyreſt</l>
                        <l>Ready to goe where <hi>Pluto</hi> dwelleth;</l>
                        <l>And, building, vainely to long life aſpireſt.</l>
                        <l>From <hi>Neptune</hi> thou the ſhore doſt ſteale away,</l>
                        <l>Incroaching on the angry Sea.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What ſhould I tell, how 'gainſt all order</l>
                        <l>Thy neighbours land-marks alwaies thou removeſt,</l>
                        <l>And from thy tenants that upon thee border,</l>
                        <l>Ground pilfers: Thou from houſe and home out-ſhoveſt</l>
                        <l>Both man and wife, that wailing beare</l>
                        <l>Their houſhold gods and children deare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet haſt thou (rich Lord) no aſſurance</l>
                        <l>So great of any houſe where thou remained,</l>
                        <l>As that thou ſhalt be kept in durance</l>
                        <l>Of all-devouring hell, and there reſtrained.</l>
                        <l>What wilt thou? None the grave can ſhun:</l>
                        <l>It takes the King, and the Kings ſonne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor was hells Catch-pole with gold bribed</l>
                        <l>Wily <hi>Prometheus</hi> backward to bring againe:</l>
                        <l>He boaſting <hi>Tantalus</hi> derided,</l>
                        <l>And his proud of-ſpring though they cry'd out amaine.</l>
                        <l>He eaſeth men caſt downe with woe,</l>
                        <l>Whether they call on him or no.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:4430:8"/>
                     <head>Ad Poſthumum. Lib. 2. Ode. 14.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>None can deny, we all muſt die.</l>
                           <l>And riches to no end</l>
                           <l>Som keep with fears, which their glad heirs</l>
                           <l>Soon riotouſly will ſpend.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>OPoſthume, Posthume,</hi> years doe paſſe away</l>
                        <l>Like glyding ſtreames. Nor pietie can ſtay</l>
                        <l>The wrinkled brow, nor olde age haſting faſt,</l>
                        <l>Nor death, that all attacheth at the laſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Not if my friend, each day in all thy yeares,</l>
                        <l>Stern <hi>Pluto</hi> thou ſhould with three-hundred Steers</l>
                        <l>Seek to appeaſe. Three-headed <hi>Gerion,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And <hi>Tytius,</hi> ore the <hi>Stygian</hi> ſtreame are gone:</l>
                        <l>Which all muſt doe that heer do draw their breath;</l>
                        <l>Both Kings, and ſilly Labourers of the earth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In vaine from bloody broyles we take our eaſe,</l>
                        <l>And from th' encounters of the <hi>Adrian</hi> Seas:</l>
                        <l>In vaine in Autumne ſeeke we to avoid</l>
                        <l>The Southern blaſts, whereby we are annoyd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>We needs muſt ſee <hi>Cocytus</hi> heavie flood,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Danaus</hi> cruell daughters ſtaind with blood,</l>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4430:9"/>
                        <l>And <hi>Siſyphus</hi> that rowles againſt the hill</l>
                        <l>The ſtone that tumbles back upon him ſtill.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy houſe, thy land, and wife to thee moſt deare,</l>
                        <l>Thou needs muſt leave: Nor to the mournfull beere</l>
                        <l>Will any of theſe trees that thou doſt dreſs,</l>
                        <l>Attend on thee, but the ſad <hi>Cypareſs.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy heire, more worthy, riotouſly will waſte</l>
                        <l>Thy Cecube wines with many locks kept faſt;</l>
                        <l>And die the pavement with high-ſpirited wine,</l>
                        <l>Better then Prelates drink of when they dine.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Ad Pirrham. Lib. 1. Ode 5.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>He ſaith, their ſtate is curſt by Fate</l>
                           <l>That <hi>Pirrha's</hi> baits inthrall:</l>
                           <l>From this gulf freed, vowd gifts with ſpeed</l>
                           <l>That he hung oth' Church-wall.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHat pretty youth, weltring in roſes</l>
                        <l>With liquid odors overſpred,</l>
                        <l>O <hi>Pirrha</hi> thee in 's armes incloſes,</l>
                        <l>When thou loves Lecture haſt him read</l>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4430:9"/>
                        <l>Ith' inner bower? Neglecting curious dreſſes,</l>
                        <l>For whom plaitſt thou the gold-wire of thy treſſes?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>How oft will he that at his pleaſure</l>
                        <l>Enioyes thee now (alas) complaine,</l>
                        <l>That he is robd of that ſweet treaſure</l>
                        <l>By angry gods, and vowes made vaine?</l>
                        <l>How will he curſe the Seas ſo ſoon that wrangle,</l>
                        <l>Whom ſuch ſly baits could not before intangle?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For he poor ſoule, deceiv'd, beleev'd</l>
                        <l>Thou wouldſt be true to him alone,</l>
                        <l>And lovely: But his heart, now griev'd,</l>
                        <l>Thy falſe inconſtancy doth mone.</l>
                        <l>His tents he in deſtructions black field pitches,</l>
                        <l>Whom thou untride, with thy fair face bewitches.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Temples wall, that's conſecrated,</l>
                        <l>To every eye the Table ſhowes</l>
                        <l>Where my ſad ſhip-wrack is related:</l>
                        <l>And how ith' midſt of all my woes,</l>
                        <l>I hung to th' Sea god, after ſtrange beſeeches,</l>
                        <l>My doublet wringing wet, and cod-piec't breeches.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:4430:10"/>
                     <head>Ad Martium Cenſorinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lib. 4. Ode. 8.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>That to his friends he nothing ſends</l>
                           <l>But Verſes: and this gift</l>
                           <l>Doth make mens name, reſound with fame,</l>
                           <l>And them to heaven up-lift.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>RIch plate and Iewels, that do lively ſhowe</l>
                        <l>The work-mans skill, I frankly would beſtowe</l>
                        <l>Vpon my friends, O <hi>Cenſorine.</hi> I would</l>
                        <l>Give them faire tables garniſhed with gold,</l>
                        <l>In-layd with Ivory, on ſtrong treſtles ſet,</l>
                        <l>Th' high-priz'd rewards of valiant Greeks. Nor yet</l>
                        <l>Shouldſt thou the worſt have, if I did abound</l>
                        <l>With thoſe things that <hi>Parrhaſius</hi> have renown'd,</l>
                        <l>Or <hi>Scophas,</hi> to theſe preſent times; The one</l>
                        <l>Cunning in colours, th' other in hard ſtone,</l>
                        <l>To make a man, or god: But, this I want:</l>
                        <l>And of ſuch ornaments thou haſt no ſcant.</l>
                        <l>Thou verſes lov'ſt: I verſes can give well,</l>
                        <l>And of this gift the worthy praiſes tell.</l>
                        <l>No marble Statues with high titles wrought,</l>
                        <l>By which both breath, and life againe is brought</l>
                        <l>To noble Captaines after they are dead;</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Hanniball,</hi> with break-neck ſpeed that fled</l>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4430:10"/>
                        <l>(When all his threats upon himſelfe return'd)</l>
                        <l>Nor faith-leſs <hi>Carthage</hi> into cinders burn'd,</l>
                        <l>Doe more his noble acts commit to Fame</l>
                        <l>(<hi>Affrick</hi> ſubdu'd, that gaind a glorious name)</l>
                        <l>Then the <hi>Calabrian</hi> Muſes. If they faile</l>
                        <l>To doe good deeds, it nought will thee availe.</l>
                        <l>Had not the Boyes name long ſince from us fled,</l>
                        <l>Whom <hi>Mars</hi> (when <hi>Ilia</hi> loſt her maiden-head)</l>
                        <l>Begot, if envious ſilence could from us</l>
                        <l>Conceale the acts of worthy <hi>Romulus?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>From <hi>Stygian</hi> rivers, <hi>Aeacus,</hi> ſet free</l>
                        <l>By powr-full skill of divine Poëſie,</l>
                        <l>Is canoniz'd for ever to remaine</l>
                        <l>Amongſt th' Heroës in th' <hi>Elyſian</hi> Plaine.</l>
                        <l>Praiſe-worthy men the Muſe forbids to die:</l>
                        <l>The Muſe men bleſſeth with eternitie.</l>
                        <l>Great-hearted <hi>Hercules</hi> is ſo <hi>Ioues</hi> gueſt,</l>
                        <l>And frolicks with him at his wiſhed feaſt.</l>
                        <l>The two <hi>Tindarian</hi> twins, ſo, ſafely keep</l>
                        <l>The Ships, though toſt in billowes of the Deep.</l>
                        <l>So <hi>Mars</hi> (his temples circled with vine-bowes)</l>
                        <l>Grants mens requeſts, and binds them to their vowes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4430:11"/>
                     <head>Ad Lydiam. Lib. 3. Ode 9.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>Though late ſome iarre did them debar</l>
                           <l>From kindneſs us'd before:</l>
                           <l>Yet ioyntly now, they make a vow</l>
                           <l>Of love for ever-more.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>WHile lately <hi>Lydia</hi> thou didſt love me,</l>
                           <l>When thy white neck I in mine arms (then bleſt) did fold,</l>
                           <l>And thou no Gallant grac't above me,</l>
                           <l>I then the <hi>Perſian</hi> King more happy was inrould.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>While <hi>Horace</hi> thine affections flame</l>
                           <l>Was firme, and <hi>Lydia</hi> thou then <hi>Chloë</hi> 'ſteemd not leſs,</l>
                           <l>Thy <hi>Lydia</hi> then, of no meane fame,</l>
                           <l>I liv'd more honor'd then the <hi>Roman</hi> Empereſs.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Now <hi>Thracian Chlo</hi>' has my heart ſure,</l>
                           <l>That ſweetly bears a part in prick-ſong, and can play:</l>
                           <l>For whom I would deaths paine indure,</l>
                           <l>If ſo the Deſt'nies would put off her dying day.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Kinde <hi>Calais,</hi> and me Love ſo</l>
                           <l>Heats with his mutuall fire, diſperſing clouds of ſtrife,</l>
                           <l>That twice I death would undergo</l>
                           <l>If for my Boy I could renew his leaſe of life.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:4430:11"/>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>What if old Love to us wing make,</l>
                           <l>And us now ſeverd, in ſtill laſting links do binde?</l>
                           <l>If gold-haird <hi>Chloë</hi> I forſake,</l>
                           <l>And <hi>Lydia</hi> my door ne'r ſhut againſt her finde?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Though he be fairer then a ſtarre,</l>
                           <l>Thou lighter then the cork that ſtill doth floting lie,</l>
                           <l>And angrier then enrag'd Seas farre;</l>
                           <l>I love with thee to live, with thee I wiſh to die.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Eadem aliter.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>In one ſtate they can never ſtay,</l>
                           <l>Whom <hi>Cupids</hi> toyes intangle:</l>
                           <l>What now they chuſe, they ſtraight refuſe</l>
                           <l>Still fickle and new-fangle.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>WHen I enioy'd thee without check,</l>
                           <l>And none more welcome did embrace</l>
                           <l>The ſnowie treaſure of thy neck,</l>
                           <l>The Perſian Monarke gave me place.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>While thou lov'd not another more,</l>
                           <l>Nor <hi>Chloë</hi> bare away the bell</l>
                           <l>From <hi>Lydia</hi> renownd before,</l>
                           <l>I <hi>Roman Ilia</hi> did excell.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4430:12"/>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Chloë,</hi> my Miſtris, is of <hi>Thrace,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Whoſe warbling voyce by skill is led:</l>
                           <l>For whom I would ſee Death's pale face,</l>
                           <l>If ſhe might live when I am dead.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Now <hi>Calais</hi> is my hearts delight.</l>
                           <l>He anſwers me with love againe:</l>
                           <l>For whom I twice with Death would fight,</l>
                           <l>If he my halfe-ſelfe might remaine.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>What if ſweet <hi>Venus</hi> doe revive,</l>
                           <l>And true-loues-knot between us tie?</l>
                           <l>If from my thoughts faire <hi>Chlo</hi>' I drive,</l>
                           <l>If my doore ope when <hi>Lydia</hi> 's nie?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Though he then ſtars be fairer farre,</l>
                           <l>Thou angrier then the raging Seas</l>
                           <l>When 'gainſt the ſturdy rocks they warre:</l>
                           <l>With thee I'll live and end my dayes.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Eadem paulo fuſius.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>The ſtorme now ſpent of diſcontent</l>
                           <l>(If Lovers words be true)</l>
                           <l>The bonds againe (ſtill to remaine)</l>
                           <l>Of loue we will renew.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHen I had ſcal'd, and did poſſeſſe</l>
                        <l>The happy Fortreſs of thy love,</l>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4430:12"/>
                        <l>And all aſſaylants comfortleſs</l>
                        <l>Tir'd with long ſiege did thence remove;</l>
                        <l>In Fortunes lap, who then, but I,</l>
                        <l>By <hi>Venus</hi> luld-aſleep did lie?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>While thou this lovely fort kept well,</l>
                           <l>And thy affections did not range,</l>
                           <l>Nor 'gainſt thee oft made vowes rebell,</l>
                           <l>Nor <hi>Lydia</hi> did for <hi>Chloë</hi> change,</l>
                           <l>No Princeſſe was more bleſt in earth,</l>
                           <l>I then did draw moſt happy breath.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Now <hi>Thracian Chloë</hi> hath the raines</l>
                           <l>Of my affection in her hands,</l>
                           <l>Skilfull in Muſicks ſweeteſt ſtraines,</l>
                           <l>And well to play ſhe underſtands:</l>
                           <l>For whom I would breathe out my laſt,</l>
                           <l>If ſhe might live when my life 's paſt.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Well featur'd <hi>Calaïs</hi> is my ioy:</l>
                           <l>He hath poſſeſſion of my heart:</l>
                           <l>He ſets me free from all annoy:</l>
                           <l>He love for loue doth ſtill impart:</l>
                           <l>For him I twice would death endure,</l>
                           <l>If him long life it might procure.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>What are our iarres if <hi>Venus</hi> ſmile,</l>
                           <l>And (cunning) with her grace-full traine,</l>
                           <l>Our mindes diſtracted reconcile,</l>
                           <l>And binde us in a ſtedfaſt chaine?</l>
                           <l>If from my houſe faire <hi>Chlo</hi>' I reave,</l>
                           <l>That it my <hi>Lydia</hi> may receiue?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Lyd.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Though he in beauty farre excell</l>
                           <l>The ſtars, the faireſt youth alive:</l>
                           <pb n="18" facs="tcp:4430:13"/>
                           <l>And thou unconſtant be, and fell,</l>
                           <l>As waves againſt the windes that ſtrive;</l>
                           <l>With thee I would in life remaine,</l>
                           <l>With thee I death would intertaine.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iulius Scaliger</hi> ſo extolleth this Ode, and the next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, that I aſſaid to tranſlate this, three waies; deſirous that one of them may give content. His words are theſe:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Inter caeteras, duas animadverti, quibus ne Ambroſiam quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut Nectar dulciora putem. Altera 3, 4. lib. Altera 9. tertij,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec gratus eram, &amp;c. <hi>Quarum ſimiles malim à me compoſitas, quam Pithonicarum multas Pindari: quarum ſimiles malo compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſſe, quam eſſetotius</hi> Taraconenſis <hi>Rex.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Ad Melpomenen. Lib. 4. Ode 3.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>Whoſe birth the Maſe doth not refuſe</l>
                           <l>To grace with friendly eye,</l>
                           <l>Shall glory gaine, by the ſweet veine</l>
                           <l>Of divine Poëſie.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHoſe birth <hi>Melpomeney</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thou ſmiling look'ſt upon,</l>
                        <l>No toyle in <hi>Isthmos</hi> him can make</l>
                        <l>A famous Champion.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No ſtately Steeds ſhall draw,</l>
                        <l>Contending for the prize,</l>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4430:13"/>
                        <l>His conquering Charet going on</l>
                        <l>With ioyfull ſhouts and cryes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor good ſucceſſe in warre,</l>
                        <l>To th' Capitoll him brings</l>
                        <l>Adornd with bayes, becauſe the threats</l>
                        <l>He batterd of proud Kings.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But waters, that their courſe</l>
                        <l>By fertill <hi>Tiber</hi> take,</l>
                        <l>And woods with leaves thick-clad ſhall him</l>
                        <l>Renownd by verſes make.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Gallants of great <hi>Rome</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Amongſt the crue recite me</l>
                        <l>Of lovely <hi>Poëts:</hi> Envie now,</l>
                        <l>With venim ſplit, leſs bites me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O Muſe, that guid'ſt the ſtrings</l>
                        <l>Of the ſweet warbling Lute:</l>
                        <l>O thou that if thou wilt canſt give</l>
                        <l>Swans notes to fiſhes mute;</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It's thy free gift, that me</l>
                        <l>Her Poët <hi>Rome</hi> doth call:</l>
                        <l>It's by thee that I breath, and pleaſe,</l>
                        <l>If ought I pleaſe at all.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:4430:14"/>
                     <head>Laudes rei ruſticae. Epod. 2.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>He many wayes the life doth praiſe,</l>
                           <l>That men ith' countrey finde:</l>
                           <l>Amongst the reſt, he likes that beſt</l>
                           <l>For quietnes of minde.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>HEe's bleſt, from City turmoyls free</l>
                        <l>(As whilome men were wont to be)</l>
                        <l>His Sire-leſs land with his owne ſteers</l>
                        <l>That plowes, and Vſurers ne'r feares.</l>
                        <l>Alarums fierce him doe not raiſe,</l>
                        <l>Nor trembles he at th' angry Seas:</l>
                        <l>He the proud gates of great men flees.</l>
                        <l>To Lawyers he creeps not with fees;</l>
                        <l>But to the youthfull Vine doth wed</l>
                        <l>The Poplar with his ſtately head,</l>
                        <l>Or elſe dead branches off doth cut,</l>
                        <l>And better in their roome doth put.</l>
                        <l>Or in the winding valley he,</l>
                        <l>Sees where his heads of cattell be;</l>
                        <l>Or hony layes up ſafe to keep</l>
                        <l>In pots, or ſheares his feeble ſheep:</l>
                        <l>Or when <hi>Autumnus</hi> head is crownd</l>
                        <l>With apples ripe in each field found,</l>
                        <l>How glad's he peares he graft to pull,</l>
                        <l>Or grapes of pleaſant liquor full,</l>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4430:14"/>
                        <l>With which he <hi>Priape</hi> thee rewards,</l>
                        <l>Or <hi>Sylvan</hi> that the fields regards?</l>
                        <l>Now under th' aged Oke he'll reſt,</l>
                        <l>Now on the graſs, as he likes beſt.</l>
                        <l>Meane while from hils the waters fling,</l>
                        <l>And in the woods the birds doe ſing,</l>
                        <l>The bubbling fountains murmurings make,</l>
                        <l>And him invite a nap to to take.</l>
                        <l>But, when ſharp winter cold doth blowe</l>
                        <l>Ith' thundring ayre with ſleet and ſnowe,</l>
                        <l>With dogs he drives the eager Bore</l>
                        <l>Into the toyles prepar'd before;</l>
                        <l>Or ſtretches forth his nets on ſtakes,</l>
                        <l>With which the greedy Thruſh he takes,</l>
                        <l>The farre-come Crane, or fear-full Hare</l>
                        <l>(His pains ſweet pay) he doth inſnare.</l>
                        <l>Thus buſi'd, who doth not forget</l>
                        <l>The cares that lazie Lovers fret?</l>
                        <l>But if his modeſt wife part beare</l>
                        <l>In guiding th' houſe and children dear</l>
                        <l>(As <hi>Sabines</hi> and the ſun-burnt wife</l>
                        <l>Of ſterne <hi>Apulia</hi> led their life)</l>
                        <l>And ſacred fire of dry wood burne</l>
                        <l>Againſt her Good-man home returne:</l>
                        <l>If the milch Yewes to Fold ſhe bring,</l>
                        <l>And milking them doe ſomething ſing,</l>
                        <l>And draw forth wine, and ſpread the boord</l>
                        <l>With th' unbought cates the Farms affoord,</l>
                        <l>No Leverine ſhell-fiſh more likes me,</l>
                        <l>Nor Bret, nor dainty Golden-eye,</l>
                        <l>In Eaſtern Seas if any toſt</l>
                        <l>A ſtorm doe drive upon our Coaſt.</l>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4430:15"/>
                        <l>I love not more an <hi>Affrick</hi> hen,</l>
                        <l>Nor the <hi>Iönian</hi> Attagen,</l>
                        <l>Then Olives ripe, that gathered be</l>
                        <l>From fatteſt branches of the tree;</l>
                        <l>Or Rheubarb that doth love the field,</l>
                        <l>Or Mallowes that good phyſick yeeld,</l>
                        <l>Or Lamb ſlain at the Land-marks feaſt,</l>
                        <l>Or Kid from the Wolves iawes releaſt.</l>
                        <l>Thus feaſting, how much doth't him good</l>
                        <l>To ſee his full-fed flocks home ſcud?</l>
                        <l>To ſee, with necks faint, drouping how</l>
                        <l>The Oxen draw the turnd-up plow?</l>
                        <l>And Hindes; the ſwarme rich men deſire,</l>
                        <l>Beaking themſelves before the fire?</l>
                        <l>The Vſurer <hi>Alphëus</hi> (this ſaid)</l>
                        <l>A countrey life then needs would lead:</l>
                        <l>Ith' <hi>Ides</hi> his mony forth, cald-in;</l>
                        <l>Ith' Calends it layes out agen.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>This Ode following, came unto my hands under the name of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ben. Iohnſon:</hi> which (for the happy imitation of <hi>Horace</hi>) I have alſo publiſhed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Ad Authorem.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>Till his Sire true doe claim his due,</l>
                           <l>This Infant I doe cheriſh:</l>
                           <l>Though without name, it were a ſhame</l>
                           <l>It ſhould in darknes periſh.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4430:15"/>
                        <l>REmember, when blinde Fortune knits her brow,</l>
                        <l>Thy minde be not deiected over-lowe:</l>
                        <l>Nor let thy thoughts too inſolently ſwell,</l>
                        <l>Though all thy hopes doe proſper ne'r ſo well.</l>
                        <l>For, drink thy teares, with ſorrow ſtill oppreſt,</l>
                        <l>Or taſte pure wine, ſecure and ever bleſt,</l>
                        <l>In thoſe remote, and pleaſant ſhady fields</l>
                        <l>Where ſtately Pine and Poplar ſhadow yeelds,</l>
                        <l>Or circling ſtreames that warble, paſsing by;</l>
                        <l>All will not help, ſweet friend: For, thou muſt die.</l>
                        <l>The houſe, thou haſt, thou once muſt leave behind thee,</l>
                        <l>And thoſe ſweet babes thou often kiſſeſt kindly:</l>
                        <l>And when th' haſt gotten all the wealth thou can,</l>
                        <l>Thy paines is taken for another man.</l>
                        <l>Alas! what poor advantage doth it bring,</l>
                        <l>To boaſt thy ſelfe deſcended of a King!</l>
                        <l>When thoſe, that haue no houſe to hide their heads,</l>
                        <l>Finde in their grave as warm and eaſie beds.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Ad Torquatum. Li. 4. Od. 7.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>Goods got with care, we ſhould not ſpare,</l>
                           <l>But ſpend them merily:</l>
                           <l>It then beſt fits, while time permits;</l>
                           <l>Which ſoon us hence will carry.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THe ſnowes are fled, the fields are clad with graſſe,</l>
                        <l>And leaves trees prank:</l>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4430:16"/>
                        <l>Times change, and floods decreaſing paſs</l>
                        <l>Not their know'n bank.</l>
                        <l>The Graces, with the <hi>Nymphs</hi> nak't on the ſtrand,</l>
                        <l>The Meaſures ſweetly dance, hand ioynd in hand.</l>
                        <l>The Yeare and Night, that cancels the fair day,</l>
                        <l>Shewes we muſt die:</l>
                        <l>Cold by the Spring, the Spring is driven away</l>
                        <l>By Summer nie:</l>
                        <l>Summer to Autumne yeelds, that pours forth graine:</l>
                        <l>Then barren Winter takes his roome againe.</l>
                        <l>Yet the ſwift Moones their loſſes ſoon repaire:</l>
                        <l>But, when we ſhall</l>
                        <l>Come where good <hi>Anchus</hi> and <hi>Aeneas</hi> are,</l>
                        <l>To duſt we fall.</l>
                        <l>How know'ſt thou, whether the great gods will give</l>
                        <l>Thee one day longer in the world to live?</l>
                        <l>Thy friendly gifts the clutches ſcape alone</l>
                        <l>Of thy glad heire.</l>
                        <l>When thou iuſt <hi>Minos</hi> doome haſt undergone</l>
                        <l>(Layd on the beere)</l>
                        <l>Nor thy high birth (<hi>Torquatus</hi>) nor thy wit,</l>
                        <l>Nor piety thee thence will ever quit.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Diana,</hi> Patroneſs of chaſtitie,</l>
                        <l>Could not recall</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hyppolitus,</hi> that in dark vaults did lie</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Pluto</hi>'s hall:</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Theſeus</hi> the infernall chains could rend,</l>
                        <l>That captive held <hi>Pyrithous,</hi> his friend.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:4430:16"/>
                     <head>Ad Chloen. Lib. 1. Ode 23.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>That there's no cauſe, from <hi>Cupids</hi> lawes</l>
                           <l>Why <hi>Chloë</hi> free ſhould ſit;</l>
                           <l>For Hymens rites, and ſweet delights,</l>
                           <l>Since ſhee's already fit.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THou ſhunn'ſt me, <hi>Chloë;</hi> like the Fawn</l>
                        <l>Miſſing her mother in the Lawn,</l>
                        <l>That trips to th' hills, in feare</l>
                        <l>Of every blaſt and breare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For, whether windes amongſt leaves ruſtle,</l>
                        <l>Or Lizards in the brambles buſtle,</l>
                        <l>Shee trembles at the hart,</l>
                        <l>And quakes in every part.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I come not Tiger-like to ill thee,</l>
                        <l>Or as a Lion fierce to kill thee:</l>
                        <l>Still follow not thy mother,</l>
                        <l>Now fitter for another.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4430:17"/>
                     <head>Ad Aristium Fuſcum. Lib. 1. Ode. 22.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>If thou, within, doe feele no ſinne,</l>
                           <l>That tortureth thy minde,</l>
                           <l>Thou maist from thence a ſure defence</l>
                           <l>Against all dangers finde.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AN upright man, and honeſt liver</l>
                        <l>(O <hi>Fuſcus</hi>) needs nor bowe, nor ſpeares</l>
                        <l>Of the black Moore, nor yet the quiver</l>
                        <l>He full of poyſoned arrowes weares;</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Whether through <hi>Circes</hi> ſcalding Sands,</l>
                        <l>Or craggy <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> he goe,</l>
                        <l>Or places where through many Lands</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hydaſpes</hi> ſtreams doe gently flowe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For, in the <hi>Sabine</hi> wood while I</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Lalage</hi> ſung without dread,</l>
                        <l>And rom'd with care-leſs liberty,</l>
                        <l>A Wolf from me unarmed fled;</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>An hideous beaſt: whoſe like ith' groves</l>
                        <l>Of warlike <hi>Daunia</hi> doth not dwell;</l>
                        <l>Nor in <hi>Moriſco</hi>'s Deſarts roves</l>
                        <l>The dry-nurſe of the Lions fell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ith' dull fields ſet me, where no tree</l>
                        <l>Releeved is with gentle aire;</l>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:4430:17"/>
                        <l>That ne'r from clouds, and miſts is free,</l>
                        <l>But ſtill doth angry tempeſts beare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Vnder the glorious chaire me ſet,</l>
                        <l>Whence <hi>Phoebus</hi> mounting up on high,</l>
                        <l>The earth with burning rayes doth beat,</l>
                        <l>And dwellings unto men deny;</l>
                        <l>I <hi>Lalagen</hi> will love the whiles,</l>
                        <l>That ſweetly ſpeakes, and ſweetly ſmiles.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>Lib. 1. Ode 26. Ad Lamiam.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>He doth declare, that thoſe, which are</l>
                           <l>Vnto the Muſes kinde,</l>
                           <l>Doe eaſe their griefe, and finde relief</l>
                           <l>From Paſsions of the minde.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I, Of the Muſes lov'd, ſad Care and Feare</l>
                        <l>Will to the ſtubborn windes commit to beare</l>
                        <l>Into the <hi>Cretian</hi> Seas, ſecure alone</l>
                        <l>Of tidings from the Northren coaſt that's blown</l>
                        <l>Of ſome King there, that's awfull for his might;</l>
                        <l>Or what ſo <hi>Tyridates</hi> doth affright.</l>
                        <l>O gentle Muſe, that lov'ſt the fountaines cleare,</l>
                        <l>Fair freſh flowers gather, ſpringing here and there:</l>
                        <l>And garlands for my deareſt <hi>Lamia</hi> make:</l>
                        <l>My praiſe without thee no effect can take.</l>
                        <l>Thee and thy Siſters it becometh well</l>
                        <l>With <hi>Lesbian</hi> Harp, and Songs, his praiſe to tell.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:4430:18"/>
                     <head>Lib. 3. Ode 30.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <lg>
                           <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                           <l>That more his name is rais'd by Fame,</l>
                           <l>For Lyrick Poëſie,</l>
                           <l>Than Kings that raiſe Pyramides,</l>
                           <l>For laſting memory.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </argument>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Work I ended have, which braſs will far out-weare,<note place="margin">The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh (as the first) anſwereth the Latin in lines &amp; ſyllables.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>And 's higher tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtately piles that Kings up-rear;</l>
                        <l>Which neither rating Rain, nor boyſtrous Northren blaſt,</l>
                        <l>Nor progreſs of years numberleſs, e'r down ſhall caſt:</l>
                        <l>On wich ne'r wingd-foot Time ſhall any vantage have.</l>
                        <l>I wholly ſhall not die. My better part, the grave</l>
                        <l>Shall not incloſe. My fame, with Ages following, ſhall</l>
                        <l>Growe alwayes green, whiles to the ſacred Capitoll</l>
                        <l>The Prieſt with ſilent Veſtall virgins up ſhall goe.</l>
                        <l>It will be told, where raging <hi>Aufidus</hi> doth flowe,</l>
                        <l>And poor in water where old <hi>Daunus</hi> forth doth ſhowe</l>
                        <l>His ſun-burnt face to people rude, that I (from lowe</l>
                        <l>Eſtate advanc't) was he that firſt of all did ſuit</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aeolian</hi> Songs and Sonnets to a <hi>Roman</hi> Lute:</l>
                        <l>Be proud, <hi>Melpomene,</hi> of this deſerved praiſe,</l>
                        <l>And binde my temples willingly with <hi>Delphian</hi> Bayes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4430:18"/>
                  <p>EPIGRAMMES, EPITAPHES, ANA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRAMMES, And other Poems of diuers ſubiects; in <hi>Latine and Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device (?) not found in McKerrow: "grain sheaf flanked by lions enclosed in circle with motto 'cor unum via una', not found in McK." [description from EEBO catalogue record of STC (2nd ed.) 2390.5 where this device appears on title page]</figDesc>
                     <head>COR VNVM VIA VNA</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Richard Moore;</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop in Saint <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church-yard, in Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet. 1621.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="verse_dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4430:19"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4430:19"/>
                  <head>AD ORNATISSIMVM virum, D. GEORGIVM CALVERT, Equitem auratum, &amp; Regiae Majeſtatis à Secretis, &amp; Conſilijs.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xcerptes varijs exhortis undique flores,</l>
                     <l>Naribus afflantes qui placuere meis,</l>
                     <l>Eque meo paucos collectos nuper agello</l>
                     <l>Connexóſque, unum in do tibi faſciculum:</l>
                     <l>Queîs ſi laeta tui ſpiraverit aura favoris</l>
                     <l>(Ambroſii quae illis roris ad inſtar erit)</l>
                     <l>Miſta roſis noster calathis tibi lilia plenis</l>
                     <l>Hortus, &amp; hyberno tempore, pulchra dabit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Dignitatis tuae ſtudioſiſſimus, IOH: ASHMORE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="verse_oration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4430:20"/>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4430:20"/>
                  <head>A SPEECH, MADE TO the Kings Maieſtie comming in his Progreſs to <hi>Rippon,</hi> the 15. of <hi>Aprill, 1617. In the Perſon of</hi> MERCVRIE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HIgh <hi>Iove,</hi> with all the gods together met,</l>
                     <l>To ſee (great King) thy comming to this Town,</l>
                     <l>The caſements large of heaven have open ſet,</l>
                     <l>And from their ſtar-pav'd floors have ſent me down,</l>
                     <l>Thee in their name to welcome to this place;</l>
                     <l>Which both thy Bountie, and thy Preſence grace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Young <hi>Phoebus,</hi> from his bright and radiant haire,</l>
                     <l>Such ioyfull light abroad here neuer ſhed</l>
                     <l>Since good King <hi>Adleſtone</hi> of yore did reare</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſtately piles with gold embeliſhed;</l>
                     <l>Which after-times (miſs-led) did rent aſunder,</l>
                     <l>And at the laſt (alas!) were fir'd with thunder.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What <hi>Iliads</hi> of grief! what dole-full teen!</l>
                     <l>What Out-cries then were heard of young and old!</l>
                     <l>What Lamentation in the ſtreets was ſeen,</l>
                     <l>As in this fear-full caſe they did behold</l>
                     <l>Theſe holy things doom'd to the fire a prey?</l>
                     <l>But at a trice the Heaven his rage did ſtay.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For, in the Deſt'nies rowles, that open were,</l>
                     <l>(Thrice ſacred King of men) they found, that thou</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:4430:21"/>
                     <l>Theſe wofull ruines ſhould againe up-reare,</l>
                     <l>And Royall gifts for aye on it beſtowe:</l>
                     <l>Nor can we think how better they deſerve</l>
                     <l>That build, then they from down-fals that prezerve.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No marvaile then, if every field and tree,</l>
                     <l>The windowes and the tops of houſes too,</l>
                     <l>With people of all ſorts repleniſht be,</l>
                     <l>And where thou go'ſt if Nymphs ſweet flowers do ſtrowe.</l>
                     <l>From every place (good King) ſee how they run.</l>
                     <l>To feaſt their eyes; and cry, HEE'S com, HEE'S com.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor were the ſluces of thy Bounty ſo</l>
                     <l>Set open to the Churches good alone:</l>
                     <l>But, it aboundantly did alſo flowe,</l>
                     <l>And to the Town by grace-full ſtreams was ſhow'n,</l>
                     <l>When (made a body Politique) they did riſe</l>
                     <l>To Place, with <hi>Hutton</hi>'s, <hi>York</hi>'s, and <hi>Mallory</hi>'s.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And though <hi>Pactolus,</hi> with his golden ſands,</l>
                     <l>Be farre remote from places where they dwell:</l>
                     <l>Yet come they not (good King) with empty hands:</l>
                     <l>For, other gifts they bring which gold excell;</l>
                     <l>TRVE LOYALL HEARTS: which thou wilt not forſake.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Harveſt ſmall, the gods ſmall hand-fuls take.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The gods aboue, thy loving Subiects here,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſacred Perſon in protection take:</l>
                     <l>And ſo <hi>Adieu,</hi> to gods and men moſt deer;</l>
                     <l>Whom, in ſuch Progreſſes, oft happy make:</l>
                     <l>And, by Heroïck deeds beſeeming thee,</l>
                     <l>Make way to th' high tow'rs of Eternity.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe verſes following, were then delivered to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, and by him moſt graciouſly accepted.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="poems_to_the_King">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:4430:21"/>
                  <head>Ad Potentiſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Clementiſs. Regem IACOBVM, <hi>Eccleſiae Collegiatae Rippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis</hi> Reſtauratore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> benigniſs. auſpicatiſſimo <hi>Maieſtatis ſuae progreſſu Ripponam advenientem, 15. Aprilis</hi> 1617.</head>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <head>Ad Regem.</head>
                     <l>SIbonus eſt Superûm Rex <hi>Diſpenſator,</hi> ut illos</l>
                     <l>Terreſtris curae non grave tangat onus;</l>
                     <l>Vivite tum coeli ſecurè Numina: Talis</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oeconomus</hi> nobis haud datus antè fuit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Angl.</head>
                     <l>If of the gods good Kings high STEWARDS be,</l>
                     <l>To eaſe them of the care of things belowe;</l>
                     <l>Then live ſecure, O heavenly Powrs: for we</l>
                     <l>So good a STEWARD ne'r before did knowe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <head>Eccleſiae Ripponen: Proſop.</head>
                     <l>Struxit <hi>Adelſtonus: Danus</hi> deſtruxit: at <hi>Odo,</hi> et</l>
                     <l>Thurston, Pontifices, mî magis ampla dabant:</l>
                     <l>Rèxque (ſacra accenſo <hi>Iacobus</hi> pectore flammâ)</l>
                     <l>Sacrilegae reddit quae rapuere manus.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Angl.</head>
                     <l>King <hi>Adleston</hi> me built, <hi>Danes</hi> down did pull:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Odo</hi>'nd <hi>Thurſton,</hi> made me beautifull:</l>
                     <l>And (mov'd with zeale) King <hi>Iames</hi> doth now reſtore</l>
                     <l>What ſacrilegious hands had rob'd before.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:4430:22"/>
                     <head>Altera eiuſdem Proſop.</head>
                     <l>Me <hi>Danus</hi> miſeram afflixit, Belloque potitus</l>
                     <l>Indigno Scotus vendidit (heu!) pretio:</l>
                     <l>Hijs ſed fata dabant ut regnis Regia proles</l>
                     <l>Gentis commiſſa haec expiet (Ecce!) ſuae.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Angl.</head>
                     <l>The <hi>Dane</hi> me ſackt, poor wretch, the <hi>Scot,</hi> o're-bold</l>
                     <l>In victory, unworthily me ſold:</l>
                     <l>But, to both Realmes a Royall ſtem, by Fate,</l>
                     <l>His peoples faults (Beholde!) doth expiate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe following, were added ſince.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <head>Alia eiuſdem Proſop.</head>
                     <l>Audijt <hi>Elizabetha</hi> meas Regina querelas:</l>
                     <l>Sed nihil auxilij (morte vetante) dedit.</l>
                     <l>Regis erat magni tantas fulcire ruinas:</l>
                     <l>Solus habes laudem hanc, Rex bone: ſolus habes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Angl.</head>
                     <l>Queen <hi>Elſabeth</hi> oft my complaints did heare:</l>
                     <l>But ſhe no help (by death prevented) gave me.</l>
                     <l>Theſe ruines crav'd a great King them t' up-reare:</l>
                     <l>This praiſe thou haſt alone, good King, to ſave me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <head>De Rumore falſo, de Regis morte ſubitò ſparſo.</head>
                     <l>Fama per attonitam ſubitò cum ſpargeret Vrbem</l>
                     <l>Ante diem te (Rex magne) obijſſe diem;</l>
                     <l>Indomito cuneti laxabant fraena dolori,</l>
                     <l>Et veluti vero in funere quiſque gemit.</l>
                     <l>Heu, pater, exclamant, Patriae eſt extinctus: in illo</l>
                     <l>Extincta eſt populi luxque, decuſ que ſui.</l>
                     <l>An quiſquam meliùs rerum moderavit habenas?</l>
                     <l>Iustitiave prior, vel Pietate fuit?</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:4430:22"/>
                     <l>Quiſquam adeòvixit cum Maieſtate benignus?</l>
                     <l>Regali miſeros ſustinuítve manu?</l>
                     <l>Heu! tantae nullus conſcendit culmina laudis:</l>
                     <l>Talem nulla dabant ſaecula: nulla dabunt.</l>
                     <l>Vera quidem falſae ſic famae filia fama eſt,</l>
                     <l>Quae mundo laudes exprimet uſque tuas.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Angl.</head>
                     <l>When Fame (great King) did through this Citie flie,</l>
                     <l>And told how Thou too ſoon a death didſt die;</l>
                     <l>All places paid to thee the wofull Rent</l>
                     <l>Of Tears, which from their grief-ſwoln eyes they ſent.</l>
                     <l>The Father of our Countrey's dead, they cry,</l>
                     <l>And with him all our ioyes doe buried lie.</l>
                     <l>Who e'r the raines of kingdoms ſo did guide?</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Iuſtice ioynd with Mercy ſo is tride?</l>
                     <l>Who mildneſs ſo with Maieſty hath ſorted?</l>
                     <l>Or with his kingly hand the wrongd ſupported?</l>
                     <l>None e'r (alas!) with ſuch high praiſe did live.</l>
                     <l>No Age hath given one like him: none ſhall give.</l>
                     <l>So, <hi>falſe</hi> Report hath <hi>true</hi> Report brought forth,</l>
                     <l>Which ſtill ſhall witneſs to the world thy worth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <head>De Eodem.</head>
                     <l>Cur populi, procerumque pias ſic verberataures</l>
                     <l>Fama per indignas te cecidiſſe manus?</l>
                     <l>Scilicet, hoc meditans, ut vivus cernere poſsis,</l>
                     <l>Quae tibi defuncto fama ſuperſtes erit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Angl.</head>
                     <l>Wherefore did Fame this wofull Newes forth ſpread,</l>
                     <l>That thou (our Soveraigne) by curſt hands waſt dead?</l>
                     <l>Sure, to this end; that thou alive might ſee,</l>
                     <l>When thou art gone, what fame will follow thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="anagrams_and_epigrams_to_Charles_Prince_of_Wales">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:4430:23"/>
                     <head>Ad <hi>CAROLVM,</hi> Augustiſsimum Walliae Principem.</head>
                     <list>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>STEVARDVS.</item>
                              <item>EST ARDVVS.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>STEWARDVS.</item>
                              <item>ARDVVS ES TV.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Aliud.</head>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>CHAROLVS STEVARDVS.</item>
                              <item>CHARVS ET ARDVVS SOL.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>EPIGRAM.</head>
                        <l>ARDVVS <hi>orbe ſuo</hi> SOL, <hi>luce</hi> ET CHARVS <hi>uterque eſt: Lucet ut Ille Polo, luceat hicque Solo.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Of the Prince his Impreſe. <hi>Ic Dien.</hi> I ſerve.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Natus ad Imperij diadema,</hi> EGO SERVIO, <hi>Princeps.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Qui bene non ſervit, non reget ille bene.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>I SERVE, the Royall Scepter born to ſway.</l>
                        <l>Hee'll ne'r rule well, that well did not obey.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad Pictorem.</head>
                        <l>Pingere ſi noſtri Pictor vis Principis ora,</l>
                        <l>MAIESTAS vultu ſit venerandaſuo.</l>
                        <l>Inſideat labijs PITHO, frontíque MINERVA:</l>
                        <l>MANSVETVDO ſuis ſit generoſagenis.</l>
                        <l>Laeta ſuos circumvolitet VICTORIA crines:</l>
                        <l>Et CHARITVM ex oculis emicet alma cohors.</l>
                        <l>Scandere ſi neque as tanta ad fastigia, dicas;</l>
                        <l>NATVRAE (ah!) Dominae cedit ut ARTIS opus!</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:4430:23"/>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>If thou our Prince ſet forth in colours fit,</l>
                        <l>Let MAIESTIE (inthron'd) in 's Countenance ſit.</l>
                        <l>On 's lips let PITHO, on 's brows let PALLAS reſt.</l>
                        <l>Let MILDNES be his roſie cheeks chief Gueſt.</l>
                        <l>Let ioyfull VICTORIE o'r his locks hover.</l>
                        <l>Let his eye-lids the GRACES grace diſcover.</l>
                        <l>But, if thy Skill this reach not, ſay; Alas,</l>
                        <l>How farre doth NATVRE, ART (her Page) ſurpaſs!</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagrams_and_epigrams_to_Princess_Elizabeth">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the moſt Beautifull and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertuous</hi> Princeſs, the Lady ELISABETH.</head>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>ELISABETA STVARTA.<note place="margin">Written before her mariage.</note>
                              </item>
                              <item>TE BEAT ARA SALVTIS.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Carmen Heroicum ex vtríſque;</head>
                        <l>Te beat Ara ſalutis, ELISABETA STVARTA.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr. de eodem Anagrammate.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Virginis intactae ſoboles noſtrae</hi> Ara Salutis</l>
                        <l>Te Beat, <hi>&amp; ſemper (Regia virgo) beet.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>The Virgins birth (O Royall Maid) Gods Son,</l>
                        <l>For ever bleſs thee, as he hath begun.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Ad eandem ſereniſſ. Heroinam.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dia cohors Charitum per te numeroſior una eſt:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Vna tenes quae ſunt omnia pulchra trium.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Thou to the Graces number addeſt one:</l>
                        <l>But, all their vertues are in thee alone.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poems">
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:4430:24"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad Illuſtriſsimum Dominum,</hi> GEOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIVM VILLIERS, Marchionem <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinghamiae</hi> Ampliſſimum.</head>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Non mores faciles, laetae non frontis honores,</l>
                        <l>Ingenij aut Genij non decus omne tui:</l>
                        <l>Externas tibi nec Iuveni data fama per or as,</l>
                        <l>Quae reducem pennis te fovet alma ſuis:</l>
                        <l>Fortunae comitata bonis non inclyta virtus,</l>
                        <l>Nec tua in Aönios munera grata choros,</l>
                        <l>Ad te oculos, animoſque trahit mirant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um, &amp; in albo</l>
                        <l>Verè nobilium nomen habere dedit.</l>
                        <l>Scire cupis quid ſit? (verborum ambage relictâ)</l>
                        <l>Haec uno pulchrè in Te omnia iuncta ſimul.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Nor generous 'haviour, nor thy browes ſweet Graces,</l>
                        <l>Nor MILDNES which thy GENIVS ſtill imbraces:</l>
                        <l>Nor FAME, which thou didſt finde in forain Lands,</l>
                        <l>And with her wings here fairely on thee fannes:</l>
                        <l>Nor vertues rare, with Fortunes gifts attended,</l>
                        <l>Nor bountie to the Muſes ſo commended,</l>
                        <l>To thee mens eyes and hearts drawes, and ith' ſcrowle</l>
                        <l>Of true Nobilitie doth thee inrowle:</l>
                        <l>But, what it is, ſoon wouldſt thou underſtand?</l>
                        <l>All theſe, in Thee alone, ioyn'd hand in hand.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poems">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:4430:24"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the ſame right Honourable,</hi> GEORGE, Marqueſs of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> upon the Acceſſion of <hi>his Office of the</hi> Admiralty. <hi>Ex Latino.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SIng <hi>Iö. Buckingham</hi> doth Seas controwle:</l>
                        <l>He Horſes rules, and Waves that proudly rowle.</l>
                        <l>So, 'mongſt the gods, <hi>Neptune,</hi> that bravely glides</l>
                        <l>Through Cryſtall ſtreames, courageous Horſes guides.</l>
                        <l>Then, let none think this double Powr unfit;</l>
                        <l>Sith even the gods, themſelves, have practiz'd it.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Idem aliter.</head>
                        <l>Let's <hi>Iö</hi>'s ſing, till th' <hi>Eccho</hi>'s ring;</l>
                        <l>For, <hi>Buckingham</hi> oth' Seas</l>
                        <l>Is Gen'rall: He doth Horſes free,</l>
                        <l>And ſtruggling Waves appeaſe.</l>
                        <l>So, 'mongſt gods high in Maieſtie,</l>
                        <l>He, that with triple Mace</l>
                        <l>The Sea with waves rules when it raves,</l>
                        <l>Guides Horſes ſwift in chaſe.</l>
                        <l>Let none amiſs then think it is,</l>
                        <l>That double powr is given</l>
                        <l>To one to beare; ſince to us here</l>
                        <l>Th' example comes from Heaven.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Idem paulò fuſiùs.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Iö.</hi> A thouſand Mermaids dance oth' Maine;</l>
                        <l>Their Vice-Roy <hi>Buckingham</hi> to entertaine.</l>
                        <l>So, he, that the proud-neighing Horſe commands,</l>
                        <l>Is Generall in <hi>Thetis</hi> liquid lawnds.</l>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:4430:25"/>
                        <l>Likewiſe, 'mongſt gods that are of higheſt place,</l>
                        <l>Saphir-hewd <hi>Neptune,</hi> with his aw-full Mace,</l>
                        <l>The mutinous waves, that ſubiécts to his lawes,</l>
                        <l>Makes ſturdy ſteeds take bits in foaming iawes.</l>
                        <l>Then, let no <hi>Cynick</hi> with his furrowed brow</l>
                        <l>Grudge at this double power that 's given him now;</l>
                        <l>Since, from the gods that raigne in greateſt ſtate,</l>
                        <l>We have this pattern given to imitate.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poems">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the Right honourable,</hi> EDMVND, Lord <hi>Sheffield,</hi> after his Recovery from <hi>a dangerous ſickneſs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHen ſickneſs late Heroïck <hi>Sheffield</hi> preſt,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pallas</hi> was ſick, and <hi>Mavors</hi> wiſht to die:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pallas,</hi> whom ſtill he harbourd in his breaſt;</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Mars,</hi> who alwayes rais'd his thoughts on high.</l>
                        <l>And if that death had taken him away,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mavors,</hi> and <hi>Pallas,</hi> both, had dy'd that day.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Which <hi>Atropos,</hi> who came with murthering knife,</l>
                        <l>Perceiving, caſt the ſame out of her hand;</l>
                        <l>And did refuſe to cut his line of life</l>
                        <l>Whoſe worthy praiſe is ſpread by Sea and Land;</l>
                        <l>And ſaid; Nay live: yea, and for ever live.</l>
                        <l>So ioy to men, and life to gods I give.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>In Bubbum.</head>
                        <l>The Sermon <hi>Bub</hi> (whatſoe'r the Preachers doe)</l>
                        <l>Into three parts divides; and then ſleeps two.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:4430:25"/>
                        <head>In Gervaſium.</head>
                        <l>A Double Gelding <hi>Gervaſe</hi> did provide,</l>
                        <l>That he and's wife to ſee their friends might ride.</l>
                        <l>And he a double Gelding prov'd indeed:</l>
                        <l>For ſuddenly hee fell ſo to his ſpeed,</l>
                        <l>That both alight, with blowes and threats among:</l>
                        <l>He leads him; and his wife drives him along.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagrams_and_epigrams">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the Right Honourable, Sir</hi> FRANCIS BACONE, Knight, Lord High Chancelor <hi>of</hi> ENGLAND.</head>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>BACONE.</item>
                              <item>BEACON.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy Vertuous Name, and Office, ioyne with Fate,</l>
                        <l>To make thee the bright BEACON of the State.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Epithaphium Radulphi Simſon, Eccleſiae Collegiatae</hi> Rippon. <hi>Choriſtae.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Spes Patris</hi> alma <hi>ſui, ſuavis luſcinia, cuius</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hac ſacra ſolita eſt vox reſonare domo,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aſcitus ſuperis paret, mundóque ſupremum</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>(<hi>Ah</hi>) NVNC DIMITTIS <hi>deficienscecinit.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ec iam virginea redimitus tempora lauro,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Te Deum <hi>Divis, atque</hi> Aleluia <hi>canit.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>His Parents hope, the quires ſhrill Nightingall,</l>
                        <l>With whoſe ſweet voyce theſe ſacred wals oft rung,</l>
                        <l>Summond to th' Saints, and anſwering at firſt call,</l>
                        <l>His NVNC DIMTLIS to the world hath ſung;</l>
                        <l>And, crownd 'mongſt Virgins, with eternall Bayes,</l>
                        <l>TE DEVM ſings, with <hi>Aleluïah</hi>'s.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagrams_and_epigrams">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:4430:26"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To Maſter</hi> Aldebrough <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>ARTHVRE ALDEBROVGH.</item>
                              <item>THOV EVER GLAD HARBOR.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr. de eodem.</head>
                        <l>Not weary to doe well, THOV doſt perſever;</l>
                        <l>And a GLAD HARBOR to thy friends art EVER.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <list>
                        <label>Aliud.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>ARTVRVS ALDEBROGVS.</item>
                              <item>SVRGIT LABOR ARDVVS.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epigram.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Turpe viro torpor.</hi> SVRGIT LABOR ARDVVS. <hi>Ille</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Quot premit aerumnis! Hic quot ad aſtra vehit!</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Sloth for a man unfitting is.</l>
                        <l>High labour up doth riſe.</l>
                        <l>How many hath that ſpoyld; and this</l>
                        <l>Aduanc't above the skies!</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the Right Worſhipfull, Sir</hi> EDWARD MOSLEY, Knight, Attorney of his Maieſties Court of the Dutchie of LAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CASTER.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This</hi> NOTHING <hi>take of him, that owes to Thee</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>All things; and</hi> NOTHING, <hi>if it greater bee.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>IAnus</hi> is come; and now begins to call</l>
                        <l>For gifts, due at his firſt dayes Feſtivall:</l>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:4430:26"/>
                        <l>But, gifts to him I none can finde to bring:</l>
                        <l>What? Are the ſluces of the <hi>Theſpian</hi> ſpring</l>
                        <l>So ſhut up? Are my wits ſo in the wane,</l>
                        <l>That the old Porter of the year, againe</l>
                        <l>Returning, ſhould me emptie handed ſee?</l>
                        <l>I rather that, which no where found may be,</l>
                        <l>In wayes before unknown will ſeek: and, Lo,</l>
                        <l>From place to place by wandring to and fro,</l>
                        <l>My Muſe hath NOTHING found. This Gift take well.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> doth pearle, <hi>Nothing</hi> doth gold, excell.</l>
                        <l>This therefore with a friendly eye beholde:</l>
                        <l>A new thing 's heere; which none before have tolde.</l>
                        <l>The Latin and Greek Poëts did rehearſe</l>
                        <l>All other things in their yet-living Verſe:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> the Greeks and Latins left unſaid.</l>
                        <l>Where-ſoe'r faire <hi>Ceres</hi> in the fields doth ſpread</l>
                        <l>Her Plentie-bringing hands from Heaven's towrs,</l>
                        <l>Or olde <hi>Oceanus</hi> (from his watry bowrs)</l>
                        <l>The broad ball of the Earth encloſeth round,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> 's beginning or end is not found.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> 's immortall: <hi>Nothing,</hi> on all ſides,</l>
                        <l>Still in the height of happineſs abides.</l>
                        <l>But, if from hence we prove the divine praiſe,</l>
                        <l>Shall we not Altars then unto it raiſe?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> 's more pleaſant than the cheerfull light.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> with beauty more allures the ſight,</l>
                        <l>Then a well watred garden in the Spring.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing,</hi> than meadowes, is more flouriſhing.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> is milder then the Southern winde.</l>
                        <l>In hurly-burlies, <hi>Nothing</hi> reſt doth finde.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> is iuſt in Peace. <hi>Nothing</hi> holdes faith</l>
                        <l>In Courtiers. And (as <hi>Tibullus</hi> ſaith)</l>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:4430:27"/>
                        <l>He happy is, that <hi>Nothing</hi> hath. For, he</l>
                        <l>Feares not the traps of wily Treacherie.</l>
                        <l>He feares not ſcar-fires that great Towns lay waſte:</l>
                        <l>Nor he, by Theeves,</l>
                        <l>or Robbers, is agaſt:</l>
                        <l>Nor he, in carefull Sutes, his wit doth waſte.</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Zeno</hi>'s Wiſeman, that doth ſo ſubiect</l>
                        <l>All things to Fate, <hi>Nothing</hi> doth not neglect:</l>
                        <l>H' admireth <hi>Nothing: Nothing</hi> he deſires:</l>
                        <l>And the <hi>Socratian</hi> but to this aſpires,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> to knowe; which now's ſought buſily:</l>
                        <l>And boyes ith' ſchoole learne <hi>Nothing</hi> willingly,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe to Wealth and Honour it doth bring.</l>
                        <l>Knowe <hi>Nothing,</hi> and thou then ſhalt know the thing</l>
                        <l>Which with a NO-SAY, eye-like, dy'd in graine,</l>
                        <l>Is in the top of learnd <hi>Pythagoras</hi> Beane.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mercurialiſts,</hi> the bowels of the earth</l>
                        <l>That rent, and with fire-belching bellows breath</l>
                        <l>Smelt metalls, and their Patrimonies mingle</l>
                        <l>With Sulphure, Mercurie, and ſmoaky Ingle,</l>
                        <l>Inſtant upon their ſecret work in holes,</l>
                        <l>Forc't in their Fornaces with hell-black coales,</l>
                        <l>At laſt with coſtly loſs ſearching each creek</l>
                        <l>Finde <hi>Nothing;</hi> and yet, <hi>Nothing</hi> found, ſtill ſeek.</l>
                        <l>No Pearch can meaſure this in th' Artiſts hand:</l>
                        <l>Nor he, the number of the <hi>Lybian</hi> ſand</l>
                        <l>That knowes, can number it. <hi>Nothing,</hi> alone,</l>
                        <l>Is to <hi>Minerva</hi> and <hi>Apollo</hi> 'nknowne.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing,</hi> it ſelfe above the Stars up-reares:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> is higher then the glorious Spheares.</l>
                        <l>And though all ornaments of Wit You have</l>
                        <l>(Searching things hid in Natures ſecret Cave)</l>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:4430:27"/>
                        <l>And gracefull ſpeech (which when you doo advance,<note place="margin">He was Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from his Maieſty touching the Forrest of Knarſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Might make whole <hi>Forreſts</hi> after you to dance</l>
                        <l>The Meaſures) and grave Wiſdome (which doth bring</l>
                        <l>You to imployment, from our gracious King,</l>
                        <l>In matters of great Conſequence) yet you</l>
                        <l>(Oh! give me leave to ſpeak the thing that's true,</l>
                        <l>And all that know you, needs muſt to me grant)</l>
                        <l>Doe ſeem of <hi>Nothing</hi> to be ignorant.</l>
                        <l>Yet <hi>Nothing</hi> than the glorious Sun-beame's lighter:</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Nothing</hi> then the glowing fire is brighter:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> doth fit each Fancie. Adde this too,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi>'s more ſubtle than the clouted-ſhoo.</l>
                        <l>Touch <hi>Nothing:</hi> and thou then wilt ſurely ſay,</l>
                        <l>Without a body <hi>Nothing</hi> touch we may:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> behold: and thou wilt ſay, that wee</l>
                        <l>Can <hi>Nothing</hi> without help of Colour ſee.</l>
                        <l>Without a Voyce, it ſpeaks, and heares; and flyes</l>
                        <l>Without Wings: <hi>Nothing</hi> walketh without Thies.</l>
                        <l>Without a Place, <hi>Nothing</hi> to goe is able.</l>
                        <l>Than Phyſick, <hi>Nothing</hi> is more profitable.</l>
                        <l>Then, try not the <hi>Theſſalian</hi> ſpels, or reeles,</l>
                        <l>When the <hi>Idalian</hi> dart thy breaſt, pearc't, feeles;</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Dictean</hi> weeds, from <hi>Ida</hi>'s top tane, prove.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> doth cure the wounds of cruell Loue.</l>
                        <l>And though thee <hi>Charon</hi> o'r his ſad flood carry,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> will thee forbid there ſtill to tarry.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> th' infernall King doth pacifie,</l>
                        <l>And bends the diſtafs of hard Deſtinie.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Titans</hi> brood, in fields <hi>Phlegreian</hi> drownd,</l>
                        <l>Than ſtroake of Thunder <hi>Nothing</hi> mightier found.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nothing</hi> without the worlds great wals doth ſtray.</l>
                        <l>The gods feare <hi>Nothing.</hi> Why then doſt thou ſtay,</l>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4430:28"/>
                        <l>My Muſe, ſo long? Than Vertue <hi>Nothing</hi>'s better:</l>
                        <l>And (to conclude) <hi>Nothing</hi> than <hi>Iove</hi> is greater.</l>
                        <l>But, now theſe ſubtle Trifles time bids end;</l>
                        <l>Leſt, if in too much paper I commend</l>
                        <l>My Verſes, unto you of <hi>Nothing</hi> ſent,</l>
                        <l>They might more Wearineſs bring, than Content.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. MILES MOODY, <hi>of an Epitaph</hi> which he wrote of the death of his vertuous and <hi>loving wife,</hi> Eliſabeth, <hi>daughter to</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. William Fawcet, <hi>Alderman of</hi> Rippon.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>ANd doth the Torrent of thy long-pent Griefe</l>
                        <l>At laſt breake through the flood-gates of thy woe;</l>
                        <l>That in a ſtreame of teares findes ſome reliefe,</l>
                        <l>Which from thy heart o'r-charg'd with Sorrow flowe?</l>
                        <l>Nor can I blame thee, that (ſo left alone)</l>
                        <l>The loſs thou of thy deareſt doth bemone;</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Like the true Turtle, that his lovely mate</l>
                        <l>(As ſhe is buſie feeding of her young)</l>
                        <l>Beholds oth' ſudden (O ungentle Fate!)</l>
                        <l>With a wreath'd Serpent ſlily creeping ſtung;</l>
                        <l>Whoſe poyſon ſhed it ſelfe int' ev'ry part,</l>
                        <l>And ceaſed not till it had ſeiz'd her hart.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Her Minde devout, her Life was harmleſs led:</l>
                        <l>To parents, children, and to thee moſt dear.</l>
                        <l>With hope of Ioy, ſhe (on her dying bed)</l>
                        <l>Vndanted, intertain'd Death drawing neare.</l>
                        <l>In Earth, ſhe by theſe vertues was commended:</l>
                        <l>Theſe were the ſtaires by which ſhe Heaven aſcended.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:4430:28"/>
                        <l>Then ſerve a <hi>Superſede as</hi> on thy Woe:</l>
                        <l>She will be abſent from thee but a while.</l>
                        <l>Meanewhile, the houres, that lingring ſeem too ſlowe,</l>
                        <l>Thou with her lively pictures maiſt beguile.</l>
                        <l>The time's at hand, when (ioynd in Ioyes for ever)</l>
                        <l>Nor Time, nor Death, ſhall powr have you to ſever.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>An Epitaph upon the death of</hi> ELISABETH BRIGGES, Daughter to the diſcreet Matron and Widow, <hi>Bettrice Brigges.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>COme Virgins, come: Why doe you linger ſo,</l>
                        <l>With ſtreams of tears that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſwoln eys ſhowr?</l>
                        <l>Her Grave with Roſes and with Lillies ſtrowe,</l>
                        <l>That of your Garland was the faireſt Flowr.</l>
                        <l>Lillies and Roſes ſoon decay and periſh,</l>
                        <l>While bitter Worm-wood and ſharp Nettles flouriſh.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Your Garlands breake: henceforth no garlands beare:</l>
                        <l>Their fading doth your fading ſtate expreſſe.</l>
                        <l>For Garlands, deadly Yeugh and Elder weare,</l>
                        <l>And branches of the ſaddeſt Cypareſſe.</l>
                        <l>Lillies and Roſes, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ye Holly-hocks, why hold you downe your heads?</l>
                        <l>And Violets, why pine you ſo away?</l>
                        <l>Becauſe (alas!) that ſhee from you is fled,</l>
                        <l>That dreſt you, and hath tane her leaue for aye?</l>
                        <l>Lillies and Roſes, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:4430:29"/>
                        <l>O <hi>Hymen,</hi> why didſt thou pale Death permit,</l>
                        <l>Within thy Right, to ſet his hate-full feet;</l>
                        <l>And take her, that for thy ſweet Rites was fit;</l>
                        <l>For Bridals, that gave her a Winding-ſheet?</l>
                        <l>Lilies and Roſes, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>When Death arreſted her, with his ſad Mace,</l>
                        <l>And clowdy Miſts her Senſes over-ſpread,</l>
                        <l>Her native favour he could not diſgrace;</l>
                        <l>Which was compos'd of pureſt white and red.</l>
                        <l>Lillies and roſes, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>All, that thy ſweet conditions did knowe,</l>
                        <l>Deſired, that their lives they ſo might ſpend:</l>
                        <l>And all, that from this life did ſee thee goe,</l>
                        <l>Deſired that their lives they might ſo end.</l>
                        <l>Lillies and Roſes ſoone decay and periſh,</l>
                        <l>While bitter Worm-wood and ſharp Nettles flouriſh.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poems">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To Sir</hi> IOHN MALLORY, <hi>Knight, after his Recovery from a great Sickneſs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OF late, when Sickneſs on thy limbs did ſeiſe,</l>
                        <l>Which Phyſicks skill could nothing help or eaſe,</l>
                        <l>And with an <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> Death was preſt,</l>
                        <l>With <hi>Non Omittas,</hi> ready theet' arreſt;</l>
                        <l>Each corner of thy houſe was fild with Wo,</l>
                        <l>And ſenſe-diſtracting Grief ran to and fro.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Which heard, the Cry oth'Poor about thy gates,</l>
                        <l>So ſhak't the doors of th'Adamantine Fates,</l>
                        <l>That by their Page th'a <hi>Superſede as</hi> ſent</l>
                        <l>To Death, to ſhew th'had altered their intent.</l>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:4430:29"/>
                        <l>For, if we take him, one of them did ſay,</l>
                        <l>How many will with hunger pine away!</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>In Matildam.</head>
                        <l>When <hi>Maud</hi> hath tane deep moultar of the Can,</l>
                        <l>She tels long ſtories of her dead Good-man:</l>
                        <l>How kinde he was to her at bed and boord;</l>
                        <l>And that he never gave her angry word.</l>
                        <l>Twixt every Cup ſhe talks, no Healths forbears;</l>
                        <l>Which her reſolves, like <hi>Niobé,</hi> to Tears:</l>
                        <l>Then ſighes ſhe, and drinks off another Cup</l>
                        <l>(For, <hi>Sorrow's dry.</hi>) then ſuddenly gets-up</l>
                        <l>(Nor can her Goſſips cauſe her longer ſtay)</l>
                        <l>And t'her dear husbands Grave ſhe takes the way:</l>
                        <l>And thither come (croſſing her ſelfe) doth weep;</l>
                        <l>Then wrings her hands, kneels down, and fals aſleep.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the vertuous, and fairely ſpreading Buds</hi> of Beautie, Miſtris <hi>Marie, Francis,</hi> and <hi>Ioane Metcalf,</hi> daughters of Sir <hi>Thomas Metcalf,</hi> Knight, <hi>he dedicates theſe Roſes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Ex Auſonio.</head>
                        <l>ITh' Spring, the Day, by fair <hi>Aurora</hi> led,</l>
                        <l>Breath'd cooly; yet the Senſe with pleaſure fed:</l>
                        <l>Quick Aire before the Faſtern Steeds did run,</l>
                        <l>Adviſing to prevent the ſcorching Sun.</l>
                        <l>Then rov'd I in a garden by a ſpring;</l>
                        <l>Where to delight me fitted every thing.</l>
                        <l>A candie Pearle upon each graſs-pile hung:</l>
                        <l>Nor ſparingly Pearles on the hearbs were flung:</l>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:4430:30"/>
                        <l>On cawles of Cobweb-lawne, glaz'd ſpangles plaid;</l>
                        <l>Which full of heavenly liquor down-ward ſwaid.</l>
                        <l>I ſaw the Roſe-beds, with trim dreſſings proud;</l>
                        <l>Which till faire Day a deawie vaile did ſhrowd.</l>
                        <l>Ith'thickets Gems were ſcattered here and there:</l>
                        <l>Which hide themſelves when <hi>Phoebus</hi> rayes appeare.</l>
                        <l>Whether the Roſe <hi>Auror</hi>', or ſhe hath dy'd</l>
                        <l>The Roſe with maidens-bluſh, t's not yet try'd.</l>
                        <l>Their Deaw, their Colour, and their Morn is one:</l>
                        <l>And both from <hi>Venus</hi> have protection.</l>
                        <l>Perhaps their ſavour's one: Ith'aire, That's ſpent.</l>
                        <l>This, neerer us, hath a farre ſweeter ſent.</l>
                        <l>One Goddeſs guides the Star, and the Flowre, too:</l>
                        <l>And clad in Scarlet liveries, both goe.</l>
                        <l>Nor ſuddenly the branches of the Roſe</l>
                        <l>In equall diſtances themſelves diſcloſe.</l>
                        <l>This bravely weares a Periwig on her head,</l>
                        <l>Her pretty Leaves are all with Purple ſpread.</l>
                        <l>From her ſquare Baſe ſhe climbs, and up aſcendeth;</l>
                        <l>And (pointed with a Rubie-button) bendeth.</l>
                        <l>Her plaited Robes this gathers in the top,</l>
                        <l>Ready to open now her ſilken Shop.</l>
                        <l>Her ſmiling Treaſures then ſhe ſheweth plaine,</l>
                        <l>And ſeeds of Saffron, which there ſafe remaine.</l>
                        <l>Shee that but now her golden Leaves did brandiſh,</l>
                        <l>Now pale (alas!) left of her Leaves doth languiſh.</l>
                        <l>I mus'd, to ſee their Beauty did not ſtay;</l>
                        <l>And, in their Cradle, that their Hairs grew gray.</l>
                        <l>Even while I ſpeake, ſee how their Glory Sheds,</l>
                        <l>And how their <hi>Punick</hi>-pride the Ground o'r-ſpreads.</l>
                        <l>Such Shapes, ſuch Births, and divers Changes growne</l>
                        <l>In one day, are in one day overthrowne.</l>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:4430:30"/>
                        <l>We blame thee, Nature, that Flowrs ſoon decay:</l>
                        <l>Thou onely ſhew'ſt them, then tak'ſt them away.</l>
                        <l>The age of Roſes but one day doth laſt:</l>
                        <l>Which being gon, their youthfull time is paſt.</l>
                        <l>Her, whom now born the Sun ſaw riſing red,</l>
                        <l>Setting, he fainting ſees on her Death-bed:</l>
                        <l>Yet her Short Life required is, that ſhe</l>
                        <l>Lives ever in her faire Poſteritie.</l>
                        <l>Pull Roſes, Virgins, while the time doth laſt:</l>
                        <l>And think how ſoon your Roſe-time will be paſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. WILLIAM MALLORY, <hi>and his</hi> deare brother IOHN, the generous and <hi>grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children of</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. WILLIAM MAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LORY, <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SEe here the Map of humane Miſerie,</l>
                        <l>The Labyrinth that you are entring to,</l>
                        <l>Full of croſs-waies of ambiguitie</l>
                        <l>Like to <hi>Maeander</hi> running to and fro:</l>
                        <l>Here had you need of <hi>Ariadneys</hi> clue;</l>
                        <l>Which in all doubts will aide and ſuccor you.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By help of it, the <hi>Minotaur</hi> you 'll ſlay</l>
                        <l>(A Monſter bred of Luſt and lewd Deſire).</l>
                        <l>And, being rid of that perplexed way,</l>
                        <l>To ſweet repoſe of minde you 'll thence retire.</l>
                        <l>Thoſe, that to kill this Monſter doe not ſtrive,</l>
                        <l>Shall (peece-meal) be devour'd of him alive.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And may not I, the <hi>Palinurus</hi> now</l>
                        <l>That at the Helm in a calm River ſit,</l>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:4430:31"/>
                        <l>Of your lancht Frigot, tell what th' heavens foreſhowe?</l>
                        <l>That happy Windes ſhall ſtill attend on it;</l>
                        <l>And that great <hi>Neptune,</hi> with his azure traine,</l>
                        <l>Will ſteer it, till the happy Port it gaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Auſonius, ex graeco, de ambiguitate eligendae vitae. Edyl.</hi> 15. begining thus;</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Quod vitae ſectaboriter, &amp;c.</head>
                        <l>WHat kinde of life may I deſire as beſt,</l>
                        <l>If Courts of Iuſtice freed from Brawls ne'r reſt?</l>
                        <l>If break-ſleep Thoughts in private houſes wun,</l>
                        <l>If home-Cares after weary Pilgrims run,</l>
                        <l>If to new loſſes Marchants be inur'd,</l>
                        <l>If Husbandmen, Want (not to be indur'd)</l>
                        <l>Forbids to loyter: if Toyle them o'r-throwes?</l>
                        <l>If Seas, by Ship-wrack, prove our deadly foes,</l>
                        <l>If Diſcontents attend a Bachlers life,</l>
                        <l>But more in vaine to watch a wanton Wife?</l>
                        <l>If Wars be bloody, if the ſharking Arts</l>
                        <l>Of Vſurers, ſuck blood from poor-mens harts?</l>
                        <l>Each Age brings Cares: none like the preſent ſeaſon.</l>
                        <l>Young Babes, yet ſucking, Iudgement want and Reaſon.</l>
                        <l>Boyes it is hard within due bounds to keep:</l>
                        <l>And hare-braind Youth fall into dangers deep.</l>
                        <l>Fortune afflicteth men by cruell Wars,</l>
                        <l>By crafty fetches and revengefull Iarres,</l>
                        <l>By endleſs troubles linkt as in a Chaine,</l>
                        <l>Still to be chang'd for worſe that doe remaine.</l>
                        <l>At laſt, Old-age, ill-wiſht-for, on us growes,</l>
                        <l>And us a ſpoyle to all Diſeaſes throwes.</l>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:4430:31"/>
                        <l>We alwaies preſent things deſpiſe: tis ſeen,</l>
                        <l>That ſom have wiſht, they gods had never been.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Iuturna</hi> cryeth-out, Why made he mee</l>
                        <l>Immortall? Why from Death's ſtroak am I free?</l>
                        <l>So unto <hi>Caucaſus Prometheus</hi> ty'd</l>
                        <l>Forbare not but on <hi>Saturns</hi> ſonne out-cry'd.</l>
                        <l>Nor ceaſed he even <hi>Iove</hi> himſelfe by name</l>
                        <l>(Becauſe he was exempt from death) to blame.</l>
                        <l>Behold the Vertues of the minde; and ſee</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hippolytus</hi> o'r-thrown by Modeſtie:</l>
                        <l>But, he that takes delight his life to ſtaine</l>
                        <l>With Wantonneſs, or baits of Pleaſures vaine,</l>
                        <l>Let him behold what puniſhment did fall</l>
                        <l>On luſtfull <hi>Tereus,</hi> or <hi>Sardanapal.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The <hi>Carthage</hi> Wars bid treachery eſchue.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Saguntum,</hi> that ſhe kept her faith, might rue.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Live, and keep friendſhip ſtill;</hi> this onely thing</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Pithagoreans</hi> did to ruine bring.</l>
                        <l>But, fearing it, <hi>Keep none:</hi> for this, alone,</l>
                        <l>Th' <hi>Athenians</hi> did uncivill <hi>Timon</hi> ſtone.</l>
                        <l>With inter-fering Cares, Mindes fraught diſſent:</l>
                        <l>That, which now pleaſeth, ſtraight will not content.</l>
                        <l>Some Honours ſeek: which, had, they nought regard;</l>
                        <l>Who, where they might command, ſtand at Reward.</l>
                        <l>When this man is by favour raiſed high,</l>
                        <l>Hee's thruſt into the mouth of pale Envie.</l>
                        <l>Still watch-full Cares goe with the Eloquent:</l>
                        <l>But unkembd Clowns do want life's Ornament.</l>
                        <l>Be thou a Patron, and defend th'accuſed;</l>
                        <l>Of Clyents Thankfulneſs is ſeldome uſed.</l>
                        <l>Be thou a Clyent, then thou muſt be ſure,</l>
                        <l>Thy Patrons words, full of commands, t' endure.</l>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:4430:32"/>
                        <l>To this man, Senators make ſute and mone:</l>
                        <l>But, ſtraight diſgrac't GRIEF him attends alone.</l>
                        <l>Poor Old-age men deſpiſe. If Heirs thou want,</l>
                        <l>Of cheating Claw-backs thou ſhalt have no ſcant.</l>
                        <l>Be frugall, and a Niggard thou art nam'd:</l>
                        <l>Be laviſh, then thou ſhalt be more defam'd.</l>
                        <l>If thou be forc't Adverſitie to beare,</l>
                        <l>Then all things elſe will goe againſt the haire.</l>
                        <l>Then, with the beſt Greek Sentence, I agree;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Tis good, Not to be born; or Soon to die.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagram_epigrams_and_epitaphs">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IOHN CAMEAGE.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou living, doſt right well, to have</l>
                        <l>Remembrance of thy death and grave.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>CAMEAGE.</item>
                              <item>AGE CAME.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigram. de eodem.</head>
                        <l>When perils I by Land and Sea had paſt,</l>
                        <l>AGE CAME, and Sommond me to death at laſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epitaph.</head>
                        <l>QVae mihi prima dedit primis documenta ſub annis,</l>
                        <l>Vrbs haec me tenuit, donec maturior aetas</l>
                        <l>Me varios hominum mores, &amp; regna vocavit</l>
                        <l>Viſere, nec rabidi vitavi vincula Turcae:</l>
                        <l>A queîs mirificè explicitus, non immemor artis</l>
                        <l>Typhi tuae incubuit pelago cum mortis imago,</l>
                        <l>Meque meoſque ferè exhauſtos ad littora fida</l>
                        <l>Chriſticolum adduxi: (ſummus Deus ille deorum</l>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:4430:32"/>
                        <l>Mî nauclerus erat) reducem me patria multos</l>
                        <l>Poſt exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tlatos terràque maríque labores</l>
                        <l>Excipiens, vocat intermiſſa ad munia vitae;</l>
                        <l>Et tandem placida hîc compôſtus pace quieſco.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>This Citie, where to learn I firſt began,</l>
                        <l>Me breeding gave, till (growing to a man)</l>
                        <l>Strange faſhions I and kingdoms longd to ſee;</l>
                        <l>Not did I ſcape the Turkiſh tyrannie.</l>
                        <l>From which delivered ſtrangely (of thy Art,</l>
                        <l>O <hi>Typhis,</hi> that skilfull was in part)</l>
                        <l>Through raging Seas (guided by power divine)</l>
                        <l>To th' truſtier ſhore of Chriſtians, me and mine</l>
                        <l>I ſafely brought. Then, almoſt ſpent with toyle,</l>
                        <l>I came againe to ſee my Countrey-ſoyle:</l>
                        <l>Where to my former trade of life addreſt,</l>
                        <l>At laſt I here in quiet peace doe reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="epitaph">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Epitaphium D.</hi> STEPHANI PROCTER, Militis.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Abſorptam tumidis navem prope fluctibus olim,</l>
                        <l>In portum docta dirigis ipſe manu,</l>
                        <l>A <hi>Circes</hi> technis rabidaeque voragine <hi>Scyllae;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Dulcis ubi aeternùm eſt nunc tibi parta quies.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Thy Ship, late toſt from Coaſt to Coaſt,</l>
                        <l>Thou ſteerd ith' Port to reſt,</l>
                        <l>From <hi>Circes</hi> charms and <hi>Scylla</hi>'s harms;</l>
                        <l>Where thou art ever bleſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:4430:33"/>
                        <head>De Poculo. Ad G. N.</head>
                        <l>Pulchra tibi argenti labris enpocula mitto:</l>
                        <l>Candida purpure is iunge labella <hi>labris.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Haec te Nectareo ſaturabunt pocula ſucco:</l>
                        <l>Oſcula tuque illis, Nectare digna dabis.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>With ſilver Lips this Cup to thee I ſend:</l>
                        <l>Which with thy roſie Lips allow to blend.</l>
                        <l>It will thee ſatisfie with <hi>Nectar</hi> ſweet,</l>
                        <l>Sweeter then <hi>Nectar,</hi> when thy Lips it greet.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Aliud.</head>
                        <l>Aurea labra tibi; ſunt huic argentea: miſta</l>
                        <l>Sint haec, ut pulchris lilia pulchra roſis.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad M. T.</head>
                        <l>Tu ſurdo cantas, das pulchra emblemata caeco,</l>
                        <l>Indoctis cum das carmina docta viris.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Thou Pictures ſhewes to th' blind, to th' deafe thou ſings,</l>
                        <l>When to th' unlearn'd thou learned Poëms brings.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Reverendo in Chriſto Patri &amp; D.</hi> IOH. KING, Epiſcopo Londinenſi.</head>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>ORphea <hi>mirari ceſſent Acherontis ab undis</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ducentem</hi> Eurydicen <hi>dulcè ſonante Lyra:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aut</hi> Amphionio <hi>fundatas munere</hi> Thebas,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dum tangit nervos artipotente manu:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fluctibus aut dorſo delphinis</hi> Ariona <hi>tutum,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mulcet dum cytharae monſtra marina melos:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:4430:33"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Coelitus afflata hijs tua</hi> Regia <hi>Buccina praestat,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Terrenas mentes ducere docta Deo.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Let men now ceaſe of <hi>Orpheus</hi> Harp to tell,</l>
                        <l>Which brought his wife <hi>Eurydice</hi> from Hell;</l>
                        <l>Or how <hi>Amphion</hi> with his Lute did call</l>
                        <l>Both Stones and Trees to build the <hi>Theban</hi> wall;</l>
                        <l>Or how a Dolphin through the Seas did bring</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Arion,</hi> hyr'd with his harmonious ſtring.</l>
                        <l>Thy <hi>Kingly</hi> Trumpet, fild with heavenly breath,</l>
                        <l>Excels them, raiſing men to Heaven from Earth.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagrams_epitaphs_and_epigrams">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sibi merito colendo D.</hi> IOANNI BENETO, Militi.</head>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>IOANNES BENETVS.</item>
                              <item>NONNE BEAT IESVS?</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epigram.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Vel tu, vel nemo eſt (Benedicte</hi> BENETE) <hi>beatus:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>NONNE BEAT IESVS <hi>te, Benedicte? Beat.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epigramma ad eundem.</head>
                        <l>Gratior est pulchro veniens ſi corpore virtus,</l>
                        <l>Cui non virtutis laus celebranda tuae?</l>
                        <l>Splendidior a facit quae ſi fortuna ſequutrix,</l>
                        <l>Quis bene Fortunae dona locata neget?</l>
                        <l>Sed dedit haec Ieſus, qui ſe dat: quo ſine <hi>Formae,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fortunae,</hi> atque <hi>Animi</hi> ſunt Bona cuncta nihil.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:4430:34"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Ad D.</hi> HIGGINS: <hi>cuius rogatu,</hi> ſequens Epitaph. ſcripſi.</head>
                        <l>Ipſe rogas (reverende) tuum que rogare, iubere eſt:</l>
                        <l>Hoc Gravitas, mira &amp; Manſuetudo facit.</l>
                        <l>Haec rogat illa iubet: ſic ſe amplectuntur, ut &amp; tu</l>
                        <l>Iusta rogans iubeas, atque tubendo roges.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epitaphium D. GVIL. TALENTIRE, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoris de <hi>Goldsbrough.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>Tu bona <hi>(Talentire)</hi> tibi commiſsa talenta,</l>
                        <l>Condeb as ſterili non malè cautus humo:</l>
                        <l>Reddebas Domino at fidus cum foenore ſeruus;</l>
                        <l>Et fidei pretium coelica regna tenes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>The Talents, which thy God unto thee lent,</l>
                        <l>Thou hidſt not, <hi>Talentire,</hi> nor lewdly ſpent;</l>
                        <l>But, as a Servant true reſtor'd with gaine;</l>
                        <l>And haſt thy Faith's reward, in Heauen to raigne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad D. GVIL. MALLORY, cum VIRGILIVM ſibi auro pulchrè ornatum dederim.</head>
                        <l>Hoc (generoſe puer) tibi do; Maiora daturus,</l>
                        <l>Si non obſtaret ſors inimica mihi.</l>
                        <l>At tibi quod munus magno maius dare poſsim</l>
                        <l>Virgilio, cuius maxima fama viget?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>This gift (O generous childe) I give to thee,</l>
                        <l>That greater would, if Fortune favord me:</l>
                        <l>But, what gift greater may I to thee give,</l>
                        <l>Then <hi>Virgil</hi> great, whoſe greateſt praiſe doth live?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:4430:34"/>
                        <head>Ad T. N.</head>
                        <l>Me debere tibi dixisti Epigramma: tuoque ut</l>
                        <l>Liber ab aere ſiem, mitto Epigramma tibi.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Thou ſaiſt, I owe to thee an Epigram.</l>
                        <l>Take this: So, now out of thy debt I am.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad celeberrimum Poëtam, IOAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEM OWEN.</head>
                        <l>En: promiſsa tuus tandem calcaria mittit</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aſhmorus,</hi> meritò motus amore tui;</l>
                        <l>Vt tibi, quem morum candor facit omnibus aequum,</l>
                        <l>Plectatur meritò ſi ſit iniquus equus.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epitaphium Reverendi viri, D. MOSIS FOWLER, primi Eccleſiae Collegiatae <hi>Ripponenſis</hi> Decani.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Coelum, Terra, Homines de re rixantur eadem:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Fowlerum <hi>affirmat quilibet eſſe ſuum.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Mercurius <hi>coelo tantas componere lites,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Deſcendens, ſtatim iuſſa paterna facit.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Coelo animam, terrae corpus mandavit habendum,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ingenij nobis clara trophaea dedit.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Heaven, Earth, and Men for one thing do contend:</l>
                        <l>Each one doth <hi>Fowler</hi> chalenge to be his.</l>
                        <l>Gods Meſſenger, from Heaven, this ſtrife to end,</l>
                        <l>Deſcend's: And thus his will performed is.</l>
                        <l>His ſoule to Heaven, his body to the Grave,</l>
                        <l>To Vs the tropheis of his wit he gave.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:4430:35"/>
                        <head>Alluſio in eiuſdem nomen.</head>
                        <l>Caeca tibi haud nomen tribuit Sors <hi>Aucupis:</hi> Ille</l>
                        <l>Vt captat volucres, ſic capis ipſe viros.</l>
                        <l>Ambo indefeſsi vos retia tentitis: ambo</l>
                        <l>Docto pellaces mittitis ore ſonos.</l>
                        <l>Intentos oriens pradae <hi>Sol</hi> cernit: &amp; idem</l>
                        <l>Cernit <hi>Neptuni</hi> veſpere regna petens.</l>
                        <l>Est tamen, inter vos, aliquid diſcriminis: Auceps</l>
                        <l>Tu captos ſervas mitis; at ille necat.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Blinde Fortune hath not <hi>Fowler</hi> nam'd thee then.</l>
                        <l>For, as he Birds doth take, ſo thou tak'ſt men.</l>
                        <l>Not tir'd with toyl, both ſpread your Nets, and mend:</l>
                        <l>Heart-charming Tunes from skilfull Mouthes both ſend.</l>
                        <l>The Sun both buſie ſees, when he begins</l>
                        <l>His race, and when in <hi>Neptune</hi>'s bowr's he Innes.</l>
                        <l>Yet this betwixt you both the difference makes:</l>
                        <l>Thou gently ſav'ſt, He kils thoſe that he takes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Lamentatio</hi> CATHERINAE FOWLER, caſtae &amp; integerrimae Matronae, in ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum morte.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Vnus erat coniux mihi, filius vnus, &amp; vna</l>
                        <l>Gnata: ſed, hos mihi tres, tres rapuere dies.</l>
                        <l>Quid deſerta querar? voluit ſic Trinus &amp; Vnus;</l>
                        <l>Orba vt terrenis coelica ſola ſequar.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poems">
                     <head>Ad D. <hi>Cradock,</hi> Eccleſiae Cathedralis <hi>Dunelmenſis</hi> Cancellarium, de Patris ſui morte.</head>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Stemmatibus Proavûm clarus; ſed clarior altâ</l>
                        <l>Virtute, &amp; iunct a cum Pictate fide,</l>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:4430:35"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cradocchus</hi> iacet hîc, coeleste ad lumen anhelans;</l>
                        <l>Lumina qui clauſit mox fruitura Deo:</l>
                        <l>Invita quem morte manet cum foenore vita,</l>
                        <l>Per Chriſtum coelo, per ſobolémque ſolo.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad Eundem.</head>
                        <l>Munera cum miſeris Dij dant mortalibus, illis</l>
                        <l>Copia non minor est: ſic imitare Deos.</l>
                        <l>Sed nil dant, niſi ſint votis, precibúſque vocati:</l>
                        <l>At tu, ſponte tua; ſic ſuper aſque Deos.</l>
                        <l>Ergo tibi ſurget noſtro Ara ex pectore ſacra;</l>
                        <l>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde tibi laudes, &amp; pia thura dabo.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Whenas the gods their Gifts on men beſtowe,</l>
                        <l>Their Store's not leſs. The gods thou follow'ſt ſo.</l>
                        <l>But, they give not except long vows compell them:</l>
                        <l>Thou, of thy Self, un-askt: So thou excels them.</l>
                        <l>Therefore my Heart ſhall ſtill the Altar be;</l>
                        <l>Whence, Praiſe and Thankfulneſs I'll yeeld to thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Pulvinulus.</head>
                        <l>Non me materies, Dominae ſed ſedula dextra,</l>
                        <l>Laudat: gratus eris ſi ſibi grata facis.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad Martialem.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pythagorae</hi> verum ſi dogma eſt, corpore caſso,</l>
                        <l>Emigrare animam corpus in alterius;</l>
                        <l>Tunc quem tam graphicè pinxiſti (docte Poëta)</l>
                        <l>Nunc eſt <hi>Lindallus,</hi> qui <hi>Decianus</hi> erat.</l>
                        <l>Nam mag is haud ſimile est lac lacti, quam <hi>Deciano</hi> eſt</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lindallus</hi> multis dotibus ingenij.</l>
                        <l>Ergo adamantëis vinc'lîs iungatur uterque,</l>
                        <l>Et cum laude illis, &amp; ſine fraude tibi.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:4430:36"/>
                        <head>Ex Martial. Lib. 1. Epigr.</head>
                        <l>If any worthie be to be inrowl'd</l>
                        <l>Amongſt true Friends, of which fore-times have told:</l>
                        <l>If any in Greek Arts, or Latin be</l>
                        <l>Well waſht, and good with wiſe ſimplicitie:</l>
                        <l>If any that loues Right, goes honeſt wayes,</l>
                        <l>And ſo to God, that all may heare him, praies:</l>
                        <l>If any ſtaid with Magnanimitie;</l>
                        <l>If this be not our <hi>Lindall,</hi> Let me die.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagram_and_epigrams">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad D.</hi> CHRISTOPH. LINDALL, Ripponae <hi>Praebendar. digniſs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>CHRISTOFFER LINDALLE.</item>
                              <item>ILEND, OFFER, CHRIST ALL.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epigr. de Eodem.</head>
                        <l>Qui bene te novit, doctiſsime vir, bene novit</l>
                        <l>Convenit ut fact is hoc Epigramma tuis.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>That with this Epigramme thy deeds agree,</l>
                        <l>They well know, that did ever well know thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>To the worthily much-honor'd Knight, Sir THOMAS FERFAX, of <hi>Denton.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>Whether thou warlike <hi>Barbarie</hi> beſtride</l>
                        <l>(That angry is with the controwling bit)</l>
                        <l>Or in calm Peace (thy armour layd aſide)</l>
                        <l>Determining Cauſes on the Bench doſt ſit,</l>
                        <l>Or doſt retire to th' Muſes thy delight,</l>
                        <l>And reads, or makes as they to thee indite:</l>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:4430:36"/>
                        <l>Whereſoe'r thou art (renown'd Knight) thou doſt beare</l>
                        <l>The Image of that Monarch great of <hi>France,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To whom <hi>Minerva</hi> brought both Shield and Speare;</l>
                        <l>Whoſe Enſignes <hi>Victory</hi> did ſtill advance;</l>
                        <l>And on whoſe Grave, with bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ter tears beſprent,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mars</hi> mournes, and Proweſs her hoare-hairs doth rent.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Achilles</hi> Friend ſo like him did not goe,</l>
                        <l>Whom <hi>Hector</hi> in his roome inrag'd did ſlay,</l>
                        <l>As thou doſt him in every point: For, ſo</l>
                        <l>His eyes he mov'd, his hands did ſo diſplay.</l>
                        <l>And, more: The Heavens this Grace unto thee give,</l>
                        <l>His Vertues cannot die, while Thou doſt live.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagram_and_epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad D.</hi> FERDINANDVM FERFAX, Militem.</head>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Pherdinandus Ferfaxeius.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>I, Prudens dux: (ah!) ne differ as.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epigr. de Eodem.</head>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Pede, Dux, fauſto: noli differre paratus:</l>
                        <l>Sic &amp; <hi>Alexandro</hi> ſubditus orbis erat.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the famous Martialiſt, Captaine</hi> WILLIAM FERFAX.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor from thy Name doſt thou degenerate,</l>
                        <l>Stern <hi>Mars</hi> his Minion, Darling of the Muſes;</l>
                        <l>Nor priſes Honor at ſo lowe a rate,</l>
                        <l>That it t' obtaine thou any toyle refuſes.</l>
                        <l>The way is ſteep, in which they muſt begin,</l>
                        <l>That Honors Fort doe Scale, Surpriſe, and Win.</l>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:4430:37"/>
                        <l>With Trumpets ſound, how ſweetly doſt thou ioyne</l>
                        <l>The pleaſing tunes of gentle <hi>Erato!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And with what ſacred theft doſt thou purloine</l>
                        <l>The hearts of men! What manly Vertues growe</l>
                        <l>From thy young Years! which ſince as I deſire</l>
                        <l>I cannot praiſe, I onely will admire.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Dialogus inter</hi> Vram <hi>&amp;</hi> Skell, <hi>duos amnes Ripponam</hi> ambientes, &amp; in parte oppidi orientali co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euntes, de morte celeberrimi viri, <hi>Ioh. Mallory,</hi> Equitis aurati.</head>
                     <sp xml:lang="lat">
                        <speaker>Vr.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>DIc mihi <hi>Skelle</hi> precor, ſolitus quite dare nobis</l>
                           <l>Laetum, cur ſubitò ſolueris in lacrymas?</l>
                           <l>An tibi quis liquidas turbavit flumine lymphas?</l>
                           <l>An dilecta tibi Nympha proterva fuit?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp xml:lang="lat">
                        <speaker>Sk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Non hoc aut illud: gravior me cura fatigat,</l>
                           <l>Noſtràque ſollicito &amp; corda dolore premit.</l>
                           <l>Nònne tibi nota est communis cauſa doloris?</l>
                           <l>Nònne <hi>Malorëi</hi> funera nota tibi?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp xml:lang="lat">
                        <speaker>Vr.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>An <hi>Malorëus</hi> obit? Parcae potuere feroces</l>
                           <l>Talis, &amp; heu tanti, rumpere fila viri?</l>
                           <l>An <hi>Malorëius</hi> obit? Fatorum O ferrea iura!</l>
                           <l>Et nunquam humanis (heu!) ſaturata malis!</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp xml:lang="lat">
                        <speaker>Sk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Illius interitu liquidis fleuere ſub antris</l>
                           <l>Naiades &amp; ſciſſis exululare comis,</l>
                           <l>Illius interitu reböarunt omnia luctu;</l>
                           <l>Quicquid habet Coelum, quicquid habetque Solum.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp xml:lang="lat">
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:4430:37"/>
                        <speaker>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Hoc fuit, in thalamo cum me ſopor altus habebat</l>
                           <l>Muſcoſo, &amp; Nymphae carmina laeta dabant,</l>
                           <l>Horrendum ut Boreas mugiens, coelique ruina</l>
                           <l>Corriperet ſtratis? hoccine cauſa fuit?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp xml:lang="lat">
                        <speaker>Skel.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Ergo, cum nobis eadem ſit cauſa dolendi,</l>
                           <l>Ambobus pariter, ſors &amp; amara ſiet;</l>
                           <l>Noſtros iungamus latices, &amp; flumen in unum:</l>
                           <l>Qui geminatus erat, ſic dolor unus erit.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp xml:lang="lat">
                        <speaker>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Eſto: ſed hac ſub lege tamen, coëamus ut ambo</l>
                           <l>In Patris Oceani liberioris aquas:</l>
                           <l>Hic dabit Amplexus, vitreóque cubile receptis;</l>
                           <l>Vt levet ipſe malis hoſpit is instar erit.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp xml:lang="lat">
                        <speaker>Sk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Gratius an quicquam mihi ſit, quàm cernere vultus</l>
                           <l>Illius immenſas qui moderatur aquas?</l>
                           <l>Hic nos excipiet: nobis lacrymando exhaustis,</l>
                           <l>In fletus ſalſas ſuppeditabit aquas.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <head>Angl.</head>
                           <l>TEll me, good <hi>Skell,</hi> from mirth to mourning cheer</l>
                           <l>What ſo hath chang'd thee, or what moves thy mind?</l>
                           <l>Hath any troubled late thy Waters cleer?</l>
                           <l>Or doth thy lovely Nymph now prove unkinde?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Nor this, nor that: far greater Grief I knowe,</l>
                           <l>Which on my wofull Heart doth heavie lie.</l>
                           <l>Haſt thou not heard the cauſe of common Woe;</l>
                           <l>The Funerall of famous <hi>Mallory?</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vr.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Is <hi>Mallory</hi> dead? O cruell Fates decree!</l>
                           <l>Could his great Worth obtaine then no Relief?</l>
                           <l>O Irow lawes of ſtill-ſtern Deſtiny,</l>
                           <l>Ne'r ſatisfied with humane Woe and Grief!</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:4430:38"/>
                        <speaker>Sk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>At his death, Nymphs in liquid Bowrs did weep;</l>
                           <l>And, ſhrieking out, did rent their greeniſh hair:</l>
                           <l>At his death, Wayling did all places keep:</l>
                           <l>Both Heaven, and Earth their mourning weeds did wear.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Vr.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Was this the cauſe when ſweet ſleep clos'd mine eyes</l>
                           <l>In my moſs-matted roome, whiles Nymphs did ſing,</l>
                           <l>That Storm-winged <hi>Boreas,</hi> and the thundring Skies,</l>
                           <l>Me from my bed ſo ſuddenly did bring?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Since both of Vs then Partners are in woe,</l>
                           <l>And neither from diſaſtrous Chance are free,</l>
                           <l>Lets ioyne our ſtreams, and both together goe:</l>
                           <l>So, that, which two-fold was, one Grief will be.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Content: but, thus; that both together we</l>
                           <l>Doe run t'our Father <hi>Oceans</hi> larger coaſt:</l>
                           <l>Hee'l us imbrace in's glaſſie Hall; and he,</l>
                           <l>To eaſe our Grief, will play the gentle Hoaſt.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sk.</speaker>
                        <lg>
                           <l>May any thing more ioyfull me betide,</l>
                           <l>Than him to ſee that rules ith' <hi>watry Field?</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Hee'l us receiue; and t'us, with weeping dry'd,</l>
                           <l>He for freſh tears ſalt waters ſtill will yeeld.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poems">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad humaniſsimum virum, D.</hi> FRAN. TRAPPES, Militem.</head>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Ne meritò videar ſterili aſsimilandus agello</l>
                        <l>(Nam data vix ſterilis ſemina mittit ager.)</l>
                        <l>Ecce tibi acceptum (Miles digniſ sime) reddo,</l>
                        <l>Vt magis auct atua &amp; Copia noſtra ſiet.</l>
                        <l>Foelix hoc foenus, quod danti, quodque locanti</l>
                        <l>Est lucro. Tali foenore Muſa beat.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:4430:38"/>
                        <head>In Rufum.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Rufus,</hi> but late returning from the South,</l>
                        <l>Knaps Southern; and now ſcornes his Countrey-mouth:</l>
                        <l>He cringes with his Face, and looks aſide;</l>
                        <l>And ſets his Countenance, as he were a Bride.</l>
                        <l>He wears a nitty Lock: his Fingers skip,</l>
                        <l>And dance Carantoes 'twixt his Waſte and Lip;</l>
                        <l>And is with Complement ſo fild to th' Brim,</l>
                        <l>That when a Gentleman but ſaid to him,</l>
                        <l>What is't a clock; he firſt his hand did kiſs;</l>
                        <l>To ſay then, <hi>At your ſervice,</hi> did not miſſe.</l>
                        <l>And as the time he intertained thus,</l>
                        <l>Before he would lay open or untruſs</l>
                        <l>The Budget of his Speech, with much adoo</l>
                        <l>A formall leg he made, and ſayd, <hi>Tis two.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ye Home-bred things, if you in's comp'nie fall,</l>
                        <l>Be mannerly; or he will ſhame you all.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poems">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad G. W. qui caſu caput ſuum</hi> Cantabrigiae <hi>fregit.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Alma foret nunquam <hi>Iovis</hi> ex capite edita <hi>Pallas,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Frangi non ſineret ſi caput ipſe ſibi:</l>
                        <l>Et tibi non fractum caput eſt modò <hi>Palladis</hi> urbe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pallas</hi> ut intraret ſic caput alma tuum?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pallas</hi> had ne'r been born of high <hi>Ioves</hi> head,</l>
                        <l>If's Head had not been broke and brought a-bed:</l>
                        <l>Was not thy Head, then, broke in <hi>Pallas</hi> Towne,</l>
                        <l>That <hi>Pallas</hi> in thy Head might take a roome?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:4430:39"/>
                        <head>In Sacrificum quendam.</head>
                        <l>A Prieſt, for Penance, one enioynd to take</l>
                        <l>A iourney with three Peaſe, loofe in his ſhoo:</l>
                        <l>Which he, devoutly given, did not forſake,</l>
                        <l>But fram'd himſelf his Penance ſtraight to doo:</l>
                        <l>Yet, that he might perform it with more eaſe,</l>
                        <l>His wit did ſerve him, firſt to boyl the Peaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poems">
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the Right Worſh. the Lady</hi> ELSABETH <hi>Metcalf,</hi> the La. <hi>Catherin Fennick,</hi> and the La. <hi>Marie Bethell,</hi> Daughters of Sir <hi>Hen. Slingsbie,</hi> Knight.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Iudge, Ladies, that are modeſt, faire, and wiſe</l>
                        <l>(Since in their iudgements Men doe varie ſo,</l>
                        <l>And in theſe caſes Women beſt adviſe)</l>
                        <l>Whether <hi>Lucretia</hi> did doo well, or no.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Virgil: Lucretia.</head>
                        <l>When with a knife chaſte <hi>Lucrece</hi> ſtabd her ſide,</l>
                        <l>And ſtreams of blood thence guſhed-forth, ſhe cry'd,</l>
                        <l>My ſpirit in Heaven, my blood ſhall witneſs heer,</l>
                        <l>That I from ſtaines of Chaſtity am cleer.</l>
                        <l>How well will theſe, brought for me, plead and prove;</l>
                        <l>This with the Ghoſts, that with the Gods above!</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Beza de Eadem.</head>
                        <l>My Bodie's ſtaind: my Soule is pure and free.</l>
                        <l>Then, from this body, chaſte doſt thou not flee?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>In Eandem.</head>
                        <l>If the Adult'rer, <hi>Lucrece</hi> did thee pleaſe,</l>
                        <l>By Death deſerv'd thou ſeeks unworthy praiſe:</l>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:4430:39"/>
                        <l>But rather if he forc't thee 'gainſt thy will,</l>
                        <l>For thy Foes fault, thou (mad) thy blood didſt ſpill.</l>
                        <l>In vaine then <hi>Lucrece</hi> thou ſeeks praiſe, at all:</l>
                        <l>For, madly thou, or wickedly, didſt fall.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagram_and_epigram">
                     <head>To M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. <hi>Dorathy Wythes,</hi> wife to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Charles Wythes,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Dorathy Wythes.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Wiſe, Harty, Doth.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr. de Eodem.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Harty,</hi> both are good:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Doth,</hi> gives them Life and Action.</l>
                        <l>Without it, both are but a Bud,</l>
                        <l>That growes to no Perfection.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epigrams_and_epitaph">
                     <head>To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Marke Metcalf.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Eutrapeley</hi> (as ſome thought) is not dead,</l>
                        <l>Though long ſince ſhe from us be gon and fled.</l>
                        <l>Shee's with <hi>Marke Metcalf</hi> gon to <hi>York</hi> from hence:</l>
                        <l>And with him there keeps dayly Reſidence.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <hi>An Epitaph of</hi> I. H. <hi>Dyer.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>He lives with God, none can deny,</l>
                        <l>That while he liv'd, to th' World did die.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epigram_and_translations">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad Poetam doctiſsimum (utinam ditiſsimum</hi>) Ioh. Owen.</head>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Vates <hi>Mecoenas</hi> olim tres unus alebat:</l>
                        <l>At nunc tres uni vix alimenta dabunt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:4430:40"/>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Three Poëts one <hi>Mecoenas</hi> once did cheriſh:</l>
                        <l>But now Three, One, for want of meanes, ſee periſh.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Aliter.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mecoenas</hi> earſt three Poëts did mantaine:</l>
                        <l>By Three, now, One ſcarce Bread and Cheeſe can gaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Aliter.</head>
                        <l>Three Poëts one <hi>Mecoenas</hi> whilom fed:</l>
                        <l>Now Three let One goe ſupperleſs to bed.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad amicum ſuum D.</hi> ROBERTVM Millner, <hi>de nomine ſuo,</hi> Aſhmore.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Littera non erit <hi>H,</hi> atque <hi>S</hi> omnino liqueſcet,</l>
                        <l>Ne quidquam nobis ſint in <hi>Amore</hi> morae.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad D.</hi> ROB. MORE, <hi>Armigerum.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Qui</hi> (More) more <hi>tuus, tuus &amp; ſict</hi> Oré<hi>que,</hi> Ré<hi>que,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>An dubites quin ſit totus</hi> Amore <hi>tuus?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Praenobili viro, D.</hi> Clifford, FRANCISCI Illuſtriſs. <hi>Cumberlandiae</hi> Comitis filio &amp; Haeredi.</head>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Ceſſent, Nobilibus ſacrae qui <hi>Palladis</hi> artes</l>
                        <l>Demunt, aut doctis nobile ſtemma negant:</l>
                        <l>Hos omnes unus vincit <hi>Cliffordus</hi> utroque;</l>
                        <l>Stemmatibus clarus, clarus &amp; ingenio.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:4430:40"/>
                     <head>To the Honourable, Sir <hi>Thomas Wentworth, Knight Baronet.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Be where thou wilt, <hi>Worth</hi> alwaies thee attends,</l>
                        <l>In Publique and in Private cauſes know'n.</l>
                        <l>Vertues thy <hi>Worth,</hi> thy <hi>Worth</hi> Vertues commends;</l>
                        <l>Which in thy Words and Deeds are daily ſhow'n.</l>
                        <l>Where-e'r thou goes, ſo let thy <hi>Worth</hi> ſhine forth,</l>
                        <l>That men may truely ſtill ſay, There <hi>Went-worth.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagrams_and_epigrams">
                     <head>To Sir <hi>Charles Egerton,</hi> Knight.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mov'd (gentle Knight) by thy great Courteſie,</l>
                        <l>And good Report I meet with every where,</l>
                        <l>I adde theſe few words to the Memory</l>
                        <l>Of Him, to whom in kinred thou wert neer;</l>
                        <l>That Man of Worth, whom lately we did ſee</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>England</hi>'s State-<hi>Atlas, Cheſhire</hi>'s Treaſurie.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <list>
                        <label>Ex <hi>Io. Syl.</hi> Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Thomas Egerton.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Honors mett Age.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Honors mett Age;</hi> and, ſeeking where to reſt,</l>
                        <l>Agreed to lodge and harbor in thy Breſt,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad Humaniſsimum virum, D. <hi>Guliel. Auſtin,</hi> Armigerum.</head>
                        <l>Ergone cum clara reſonet tua Buccina voce,</l>
                        <l>Auribus obstreperet noſtra Cicuta tuis?</l>
                        <l>Sed ita vis; neque detrecto: Sic <hi>Daulias</hi> ipſa</l>
                        <l>Carmen iners audit non variantis avis.</l>
                        <l>Stridulus arguto ſic garriat Anſer Olori:</l>
                        <l>Sicque Cicada tuis O Galerita ſonis.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:4430:41"/>
                        <head>Ad Ornatiſsimum Virum, D. <hi>Guidonem Palmes,</hi> Militem.</head>
                        <l>Corporis, aut Animi, ſi quis Bona ponderet, inter</l>
                        <l>Millia multa virûm <hi>Palmes</hi> tibi Palma datur.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>If Ornaments thou of the Minde,</l>
                        <l>Or Bodie in the Weigh-ſcales ſet,</l>
                        <l>'Mongſt many Thouſands thou'll not finde</l>
                        <l>One, that from <hi>Palmes</hi> the Palm can get.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad Reverendum virum, D. Doctorem FAVOR.</head>
                        <l>Eſt <hi>Favor</hi> in vultu: verbis <hi>Favor</hi> ipſe relucet:</l>
                        <l>Corpore pars toto nulla <hi>Favore</hi> vacat.</l>
                        <l>Non mirum est igitur ſi ſint ea plena <hi>Favore</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Quae facias, cum ſis Totus &amp; ipſe <hi>Favor.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad Inſignem Poëtam, D. <hi>Ben. Iohnſon.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>Ne ſit iners impunè, tuus titubétve Caballus,</l>
                        <l>Munera <hi>Mulciberi</hi> mitto polita manu.</l>
                        <l>Nève tuus langueſcat amor, tibi Carmina mitto:</l>
                        <l>Sic Pauper diti poma dat <hi>Alcinoö.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Ad D.</hi> Franckland.</head>
                        <l>Sit tibi terra ferax (omni feritate relictâ)</l>
                        <l>Qui candore animi notus es eſſe ferax.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>Still let the <hi>Land</hi> be <hi>Frank</hi> to thee,</l>
                        <l>(All rudeneſs ſet aſide)</l>
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:4430:41"/>
                        <l>Whoſe Frankneſs in all Courteſie</l>
                        <l>So well is know'n and try'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad <hi>Hen. Bethell,</hi> D. <hi>Gualteri Bethell,</hi> Militis filium, cum <hi>Iuſtinianum</hi> ſibi mitterem.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Vis fieri Doctus? vis Dives?</hi> Iuſtinianum</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Perlege: Doctrinam, Divitiáſque dabit.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>If Learning thou, or Riches would'ſt obtaine,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> reade: By him thou both mayſt gaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Ad D. <hi>Io: Davies,</hi> Milite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iudicem Itinerariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Si tua legiſſet redivivus Carmina</hi> Plato,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Queîs Animae dotes</hi> Entheus <hi>ipſe canis:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aut tua voluiſſet</hi> Bilbili <hi>Epigrammata Vates,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Tempora queîs ſalſe liberiora notas;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Diverſo quamvis Genio ſcripſere hic, &amp; ille,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Traderet hic Palmam, traderet ille tibi.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>If <hi>Plato</hi> liv'd, and ſaw thoſe Heaven-breath'd Lines</l>
                        <l>Where thou the Eſſence of the Soule confines,</l>
                        <l>Or merry <hi>Martiall</hi> read thy Epigrammes</l>
                        <l>Where ſportingly theſe looſer times thou blames;</l>
                        <l>Though both excell, yet (in their ſeverall wayes)</l>
                        <l>They both, ore-come, would yeeld to thee the Praiſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Ad D.</hi> Thomam Beſt.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>An quiſquam neget hunc foelici ſydere natum,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Qui ſolet in quo vis</hi> Optimus <hi>eſse loco?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>With happy ſtars he ſure is Bleſt,</l>
                        <l>Whereſoe'r he goes that ſtill is <hi>Best.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epigrams_epitaphs_and_anagrams">
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:4430:42"/>
                     <head>To Miſtris <hi>Katherin Dutton,</hi> Daughter of M. <hi>Dutton,</hi> the worthy Alderman of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> lately deceaſed.</head>
                     <list>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Katherine Dutton.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>That kind true one.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>A Woman <hi>kinde,</hi> that is not <hi>True,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Playes falſe, and makes her Husband rue:</l>
                        <l>If <hi>True</hi> ſhe be, and nothing <hi>Kinde,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Shee is a Corraſiue to his Minde.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>True kindneſs,</hi> and <hi>Kinde Truth</hi> in one,</l>
                        <l>Make-up a happy Vnion.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Epitaphium</hi> Robini.</head>
                        <l>Round <hi>Robin</hi>'s gone: And this Grave doth incloſe</l>
                        <l>The Pudding of his Doublet and his Hoſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Ad D.</hi> Iohannem Petty, <hi>de quodam</hi> Male.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sit malè</hi> (Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>) <hi>tibi, ſi ſis malus, atque moleſtus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Atque malo petus ſit Tibi</hi> (Male) <hi>precor:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sin (magè quod cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o) tu ſis bonus, atque benignus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Opto ut contingat nil tibi</hi> (Male) <hi>mali.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>In Fidicinem infidum.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Non tibi danda fides, Fidicen: diſcrimine nullo</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Túque fides violas, tu violaſque fidem.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Aliud.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Qui fidibus ludis, volupe est tibi ludere amicos:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Est eadem fidei cura fidiſque tibi.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Dominus quidam de ſe.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Poſcenti ſoleo nummos iraſcter: An quod</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Do Minus <hi>atque</hi> Minas, <hi>dicor ego</hi> Dominus?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:4430:42"/>
                        <head>To M. <hi>Chriſtopher Moyſer.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>The Friendſhip, that betwixt us is begun</l>
                        <l>For cauſes iuſt (which we our ſelves beſt knowe)</l>
                        <l>Will for the ſame I truſt on ſmoothly run,</l>
                        <l>And with the time increaſe, and greater growe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <list>
                        <head>Ad Reverendum virum, ſibique meritò colendum, Ad D. <hi>Hodgſon,</hi> ſacrae Theologiae Doctorem.</head>
                        <label>Anagr.</label>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Phineas Hodgſonius, Doctor.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Dignus Honore dato, poſcis.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dignus Honore dato meritò tu poſcis Honorem:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Qui datur indigno, non honor eſt, at onus.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Of One that (wearing an Hawthorne in his hat to ſave him from the thunder) was ſuſpected, upon Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination found to be a Prieſt, and is now in Priſon. <hi>In Sacriſicum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Albo Sacrificus ſpino ſua tempora cinxit,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sic</hi> Iovis <hi>ut ſugeret fulmina miſſa manu:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Caeſaris <hi>at non ſic effugit fulmina laeſi.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Diviſum Imperium cum <hi>love Caeſar</hi> habet.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>A Prieſt, that he <hi>Ioves</hi> thunder might not feare,</l>
                        <l>An Hawthorn garland on his head did weare:</l>
                        <l>Which him from <hi>Caeſars</hi> thunder could not hide.</l>
                        <l>Caeſar <hi>with</hi> Iove <hi>Dominion doth divide:</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg xml:lang="lat">
                        <head>In Eundem.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fulmina dum vitas, invitas fulmina demens:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Interior a Deo, haud exterior a placent.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:4430:43"/>
                        <head>Angl.</head>
                        <l>While fondly thou the Thunder ſhuns</l>
                        <l>Vpon the Thunder-bolt thou runs:</l>
                        <l>For, ſurely God (whom all ſhould praiſe)</l>
                        <l>Not outward things, but inward pleaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Paget.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>Our Friendſhip ſtrengthned by continuance,</l>
                        <l>And the reſpect that to thy worth is fit,</l>
                        <l>Claim in my Writings this rememberance,</l>
                        <l>That each Page ſhould <hi>Iohn Paget</hi> haue in it.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>In Tortum.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Tortus,</hi> accus'd to lie, to feine, and flatter,</l>
                        <l>Said, he but ſet a good Face on the matter.</l>
                        <l>Then ſure, he borrow'd it: for (tis well knowne)</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Tortus</hi> ne'r wore a good Face of his owne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>De Seipſo.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Surety,</hi> what's that? I to my loſs have try'd,</l>
                        <l>Who for anothers Debt too <hi>Sure</hi> am <hi>Ty</hi>'d:</l>
                        <l>If this I had Etymologiz'd before,</l>
                        <l>I never had been ſhut within this doore.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="verse_dedication">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:4430:43"/>
                  <head>GENERIS SPLENDORE, Doctrina, &amp; Pietate viro praecellenti, <hi>D.</hi> THOMAE WHARTON, <hi>Equiti</hi> aurato, D. <hi>Philippi</hi> Baronis de <hi>Wharton,</hi> Filio &amp; Haeredi.</head>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccipe, ſed placidus, de laude haec carmina Ruris</l>
                     <l>(Aulae &amp; nunc ruris, non mediocre decus)</l>
                     <l>Dum facili aggredior fiſcellam texere hibiſco,</l>
                     <l>Quae modò dictavit ruſtica Muſa mihi.</l>
                     <l>Sic tua (foeminei laus, &amp; nova gloria, ſexus)</l>
                     <l>Pignoribus ditet te <hi>Philadelpha</hi> xthori:</l>
                     <l>Sicque tuus, pulchrâ pulcher qui ludit in Aulâ,</l>
                     <l>Te clara faciat prole <hi>Philippus</hi> Avum.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Angl.</head>
                     <l>ACcept theſe Lines, the Countrie's praiſe that tell</l>
                     <l>(O thou the Court's and Country's dear Delight)</l>
                     <l>Which, as I Mawnds made in my homely Cell,</l>
                     <l>My Countrey Muſe did late to me indite.</l>
                     <l>So, let thy <hi>Philadelph</hi> (her Sexes praiſe)</l>
                     <l>Enrich thee ſtill with Treaſures of her bed:</l>
                     <l>So, let thy <hi>Philip,</hi> in thy Hall that playes,</l>
                     <l>Thee Grandfire make by Iſſue fairely ſpred.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Virtutum tuarum cultor obſervantiſsimus, IOH: ASHMORVS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4430:44"/>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:4430:44"/>
                  <head>THE PRAISE OF A COVNTRY LIFE. MARTIAL. Lib. 4. Epigram. 90. <hi>De Ruſticatione.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Sks thou, ith' Country how I ſpend the Day?</l>
                     <l>Early, each morning, to the gods I pray.</l>
                     <l>My Servants then, and Fields to ſee I goe,</l>
                     <l>And every one appoint what worke to doe.</l>
                     <l>This done, I read, and Vows to <hi>Phoebus</hi> make</l>
                     <l>To eaſe me, and my drouping Muſe t'awake.</l>
                     <l>My Body then I rub and ore-anoynt,</l>
                     <l>And eaſily ſtretch-out each Lim and Ioynt,</l>
                     <l>Reioycing in my mind, ſecure and free</l>
                     <l>From debt, and the black books of Vſurie.</l>
                     <l>I dine, I drink, I ſing, I waſh, I play,</l>
                     <l>I ſup; then, from my Reſt not long do ſtay:</l>
                     <l>Yet, till my Lampe a little Oyle doe ſpend,</l>
                     <l>Som time I nightly to the Muſes lend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>VIRGIL. <hi>Georg.</hi> lib. 2. <hi>Vitae Rusticae Laus.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O Happy (if their Happineſs they knew)</l>
                        <l>Are Husbandmen; to whom, in ſeaſons due</l>
                        <l>(Far from <hi>Bellona</hi>'s Rage in bloody Fields)</l>
                        <l>The thankfull Earth food from her Boſome yeelds.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:4430:45"/>
                        <l>If their proud Gates from each Room belch not out</l>
                        <l>Of Smell-feaſt Paraſites a fleering Rout;</l>
                        <l>Nor Pillars they deſire, that bear on high</l>
                        <l>Roofs fairly fretted with Imagery;</l>
                        <l>Nor Clothes, where ſcattred Gold ſportes interlaced;</l>
                        <l>Nor Plate of <hi>Corinth</hi> curiouſly enchaſed;</l>
                        <l>Nor their white Fleeces are with Venim foil'd;</l>
                        <l>Nor ſelf-pure Oyl with Slibber-ſawces ſpoil'd:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet quiet Reſt, and harm-leſs Lives they have</l>
                        <l>So rich of good things, that they need not crave;</l>
                        <l>And ſpatious Grounds, where they doo walk at leaſure;</l>
                        <l>And Caves, and Springs, and Woods, and Groves, for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</l>
                        <l>Their bellowing Oxen, and their bleating Sheep,</l>
                        <l>In ſome cool Shade them ſummon to ſweet Sleep:</l>
                        <l>There Forreſts, and there Dens of wilde Beaſts are,</l>
                        <l>And Youth enduring toil with little Fare;</l>
                        <l>There holy Rites, and holy Fathers been:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> leaving th' Earth, There laſt was ſeen.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But, firſt let the ſweet Muſes (whom above</l>
                        <l>All other things I moſt eſteem and love)</l>
                        <l>Mee entertain their Prieſt, and to mee ſhowe</l>
                        <l>The Circuits that the Heav'ns and Stars doo go,</l>
                        <l>The ſundr' Eclipſes of the Sun and Moon,</l>
                        <l>Whence Earth-quakes come; what Powr the Sea ſo ſoon</l>
                        <l>(His Bars broke down) makes proudly rage and ſwell,</l>
                        <l>And brings it back, within its Banks to dwell:</l>
                        <l>Why Winter-daies ſo faſt doo run away,</l>
                        <l>And why the lingering Nights ſo long doo ſtay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But, if dull Blood, congeal'd about my Hart,</l>
                        <l>Forbids mee t' undergo this worthy Part</l>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:4430:45"/>
                        <l>Of Natures Worth; Then let the Country pleaſe-mee,</l>
                        <l>And Rivers (running through the Vallies) eaſe-mee.</l>
                        <l>Then let mee love the Woods and Floods unknowne.</l>
                        <l>O that there were, O that there were but one</l>
                        <l>That would mee ſet upon the pleaſant Plain,</l>
                        <l>By which ſwift <hi>Pirchius</hi> doth his Courſe maintain</l>
                        <l>With poſting Waters! or on <hi>Taget</hi> Hill,</l>
                        <l>Which <hi>Spartan</hi> Virgins with mad Shriekings fill</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Bacchus</hi> Feaſts! or, under <hi>Hemus</hi> Bank,</l>
                        <l>Would cover me ith' Shade of Branches rank!</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hee's happy, that the Cauſes of things knowes,</l>
                        <l>That vanquiſheth, and at his Feet down throwes,</l>
                        <l>All Cares, and Deſt'nies unappeas'd Miſ-haps,</l>
                        <l>And th' hideous Noiſe of Hel's ſtill-gaping Chaps.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hee's happy too, the Country-gods that knoweth;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pan,</hi> and <hi>Sylvanus</hi> (that in Yeers now groweth)</l>
                        <l>And ſiſter-Fairies, tripping on the Lawn.</l>
                        <l>He, from his ſettled Life, will not bee drawn</l>
                        <l>By Honours Enſignes, nor by Robes of State,</l>
                        <l>Nor by ambitious Thoughts that hatch Debate,</l>
                        <l>And faith-leſſe Brethren ſetteth by the Ears;</l>
                        <l>Nor Treachery, amaz'd with doubtfull Fears;</l>
                        <l>Nor by <hi>Rome</hi>'s Glory (that now beareth Sway)</l>
                        <l>Nor Kingdoms, that ſoon periſh and decay.</l>
                        <l>Hee pulingly ne'r mourneth for the Poor,</l>
                        <l>Nor him envieth that is rich in Store.</l>
                        <l>The Fruit, his Trees and Ground yeeld willingly,</l>
                        <l>Hee gathers, and hee keepeth carefully:</l>
                        <l>Nor doth hee hard and cruell Lawes behould,</l>
                        <l>Now brawling Courts, where Iudgements are inroul'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:4430:46"/>
                        <l>Some, Seas vnknowne with Oares moleſt, nor ſhun</l>
                        <l>They murthering Steele: to Princes Courts Some run.</l>
                        <l>He Cities ſackes, and Matrones makes to weepe,</l>
                        <l>That hee may bowze in Pearle, in Purple ſleepe.</l>
                        <l>From Riches hid, Another ſeldom flitteth;</l>
                        <l>But, on his buried Gold (as brooding) ſitteth.</l>
                        <l>He, at the Barre ſtruck mute, aſtoniſht ſtands:</l>
                        <l>Gaping for Praiſe, Him Shouts, and Claps of hands</l>
                        <l>Ith' Theater (for, they redoubled be</l>
                        <l>By Senators, and the Plebeïty)</l>
                        <l>Raiſe like a Top, and turn-ſick make with Pride.</l>
                        <l>Theſe Swaggerers hands theirs Brothers bloud have dy'd.</l>
                        <l>From place to place Theſe ſtill do trudge and range,</l>
                        <l>And their ſweet Homes for Baniſhment do change:</l>
                        <l>New fangled, from their truſty Friends they run,</l>
                        <l>To ſeeke a Place warm'd with another Sun.</l>
                        <l>The Husband-man with crookt Plough doth not ſpare</l>
                        <l>To ſtir his Ground. Hence, his Revenewes are:</l>
                        <l>Hence, to his Country, Scot and Lot hee paies:</l>
                        <l>Hence, Suſt'nance for his Houſhould hee doth raiſe,</l>
                        <l>And his young Nephews: Hence, hee doth preſerve</l>
                        <l>His Heards of Beaſts; and Steers, that wel dezerve.</l>
                        <l>Nor will it reſt, but th' Yeer will ſet abroad</l>
                        <l>His Riches, and each Bough with Fruit will load;</l>
                        <l>Or great Increaſe will Cattell cauſe to yield,</l>
                        <l>Or <hi>Ceres</hi> Gifts ſo ſhed in every Field,</l>
                        <l>That ſcarce the Furrows may their Burden bear,</l>
                        <l>And their large Barns aſunder that will tear.</l>
                        <l>Winter draws on. The Olive-berries then</l>
                        <l>They grinde in Mills: The Hogs come home agen</l>
                        <l>Frolick with Maſt and Wildings in the Woods.</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Autumn</hi> is no Niggard of his Goods:</l>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:4430:46"/>
                        <l>The Veſſels hee to th' Brimmes with ripe Grapes fils,</l>
                        <l>And preſſeth them forth on the ſun-ſhine Hils.</l>
                        <l>Mean-while, their pretty Babes they hugge and kiſs:</l>
                        <l>Milde Chaſtity ſtill their Houſe-keeper is.</l>
                        <l>The Kine with ſtrouting Vdders come to th' Pail:</l>
                        <l>The wanton Kids (ith' rank Graſs, by) aſſail,</l>
                        <l>With Horns new put-forth, proudly one another:</l>
                        <l>Nor to the Gods, unthankfull, doth hee ſmother</l>
                        <l>Their Gifts; but keeps his Feaſts Solemnities,</l>
                        <l>And on the Graſs with Flowres embrodered lies;</l>
                        <l>Where, in the midſt, the Fire they compaſs round,</l>
                        <l>When his Help-fellows quaffing Boawls have crownd:</l>
                        <l>Which lightly toucht, with Vowes hee calls on thee,</l>
                        <l>O <hi>Bacchus.</hi> Then hee Games, for Maſtery,</l>
                        <l>In th' Elm to Neat-heards ſets: Hee, that ſhoots beſt,</l>
                        <l>Muſt have the Shout and Praiſe from all the reſt.</l>
                        <l>Their leather-Pelts put-off, the thick-skin Crew</l>
                        <l>Themſelves in untaught Wraſtling tugge and tew.</l>
                        <l>Long-ſince, the ancient <hi>Sabines</hi> lived thus:</l>
                        <l>Thus <hi>Remus,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Romulus:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Warlick <hi>Hetruria</hi> thus to Greatnes grew:</l>
                        <l>Yea, <hi>Rome</hi> herſelf (to whom all Nations ſue,</l>
                        <l>Th' admired Minion of the World) thus roſe,</l>
                        <l>And in one Wall ſeaven Towres did thus incloſe.</l>
                        <l>And, long before the <hi>Cretian</hi> King did raign,</l>
                        <l>And cruell People liv'd by Bullocks ſlain,</l>
                        <l>Good <hi>Saturn</hi> thus on Earth did ſpend his Daies:</l>
                        <l>Fearfull Alarums yet men did not raiſe</l>
                        <l>To hatefull Wars; nor (on hard Anvils wrought</l>
                        <l>With crackling noiſe) for ſlaughter Swords were ſought.</l>
                        <l>But now, ith' Wilde-gooſe-Chaſe o'r-hal'd with Pains,</l>
                        <l>'Tis time to looſe my froathing Horſes Rains.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:4430:47"/>
                     <head>Ex <hi>M. Antonio Flaminio,</hi> ad Agellum ſuum. Sic incipit: <hi>Vmbrae frigidulae, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>COol Shades, Air-fanning Groves,</l>
                        <l>With your ſoft Whiſperings,</l>
                        <l>Where Pleaſure ſmiling roves</l>
                        <l>Through deawie Caves &amp; Springs,</l>
                        <l>And bathes her purple Wings:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With Flowrs inameld Ground</l>
                        <l>(Nature's fair Tapeſtry)</l>
                        <l>Where chattering Birds abound,</l>
                        <l>Flickring from Tree to Tree,</l>
                        <l>With Change of Melody:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sweet Liberty and Leaſures,</l>
                        <l>Where ſtill the Muſes keep,</l>
                        <l>O! if to thoſe true Treaſures,</l>
                        <l>That from your Boſoms peep,</l>
                        <l>I might ſecurely creep:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If I might ſpend my Daies</l>
                        <l>(Remote from publike Brawls)</l>
                        <l>Now tuning lovely Laies,</l>
                        <l>Now light-foot Madrigals,</l>
                        <l>Ne'r checkt with ſudden Calls:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now follow Sleep that goes</l>
                        <l>Ruſtling ith' green-wood Shade;</l>
                        <l>Now milk my Goat, that knowes</l>
                        <l>(With her yong fearfull Cade)</l>
                        <l>The Pail ith' cooly Glade,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="87" facs="tcp:4430:47"/>
                        <l>And with Boawls fild to th' Brims</l>
                        <l>Of milky Moiſture new,</l>
                        <l>To water my dry'd Lims,</l>
                        <l>And t' all the wrangling Crew</l>
                        <l>Of Cares to bid, <hi>Adew;</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What Life then ſhould I lead!</l>
                        <l>How like then would it bee</l>
                        <l>Vnto the Gods, that tread</l>
                        <l>Ith' ſtarry Gallery</l>
                        <l>Of true Felicity!</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But you, O Virgins ſweet,</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Helicon</hi> thar dwell,</l>
                        <l>That oft the Fountains greet,</l>
                        <l>When you the Pleaſures tell</l>
                        <l>Ith' Country that excell:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If I my Life, though dear,</l>
                        <l>For your far dearer ſake,</l>
                        <l>To yeeld would nothing fear;</l>
                        <l>From Citie's Tumults take-mee,</l>
                        <l>And free ith' Country make-mee.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="verse_dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4430:48"/>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:4430:48"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. RICHARD HVTTON, <hi>Knight, one of his Maieſties</hi> Iuſtices in the Court of <hi>Common Pleas.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F my Hopes harveſt, <hi>Worthy Sir,</hi> had not</l>
                     <l>Been blaſted with the Breath of dull Deſpaire,</l>
                     <l>My Muſe (ne'r branded with the hatefull blot</l>
                     <l>Of cheap Ingratitude, freed from baſe Care)</l>
                     <l>The Tribute of her Love (for Cauſes iuſt)</l>
                     <l>Would not ſo long have ſmothered in the Duſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet lookes Shee for one Sun-ſhine Day: Mean while,</l>
                     <l>Accept theſe Gleanings, gathered in the Fields</l>
                     <l>Of good Free-holders, in the bleſſed <hi>Ile,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where each one ſhewes (as his Affection yeelds)</l>
                     <l>Who is moſt bleſt: which none can better tell,</l>
                     <l>Then the ſweet Singer doth of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips, in his beſt indeavors to command, IOH: ASHMORE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poems">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4430:49"/>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:4430:49"/>
                  <head>OF A BLESSED LIFE. MARTIALIS, <hi>ad ſeipſum, vel potius ad</hi> Iulium Martialem. <hi>Lib. 10. Epigr.</hi> 47.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Merrie <hi>Martial,</hi> I miſtake,</l>
                     <l>A happy Life if theſe not make;</l>
                     <l>Riches bequeath'd, not got by toyle,</l>
                     <l>A fire ne'r out, no barren Soyle,</l>
                     <l>No Strife, ſeld' Office, a Minde found</l>
                     <l>Still calme, fit Strength, a Body ſound,</l>
                     <l>Wiſe Smpleneſs, Friends equall bred,</l>
                     <l>No coſtly Fare, a Boord ſoon ſpred,</l>
                     <l>Nights never drunk, but from Cares free,</l>
                     <l>A gameſome Bed with Modeſtie,</l>
                     <l>Sleep making Darkneſs ſhort to bee.</l>
                     <l>Be with thy State Content: ſo ſtay:</l>
                     <l>Wiſh not, nor feare, thy Fatall-Day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Strigillius</hi> contra <hi>Martialem.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>O Trifling <hi>Martial,</hi> tis moſt ſure</l>
                     <l>That theſe things a bleſt Life procure:</l>
                     <l>Senſe of our Sinne, an Heart relenting,</l>
                     <l>Griefe for our errors, Tears repenting,</l>
                     <l>And Faith, that ſaving Health embraceth.</l>
                     <l>For, he that on this ſure Rock placeth</l>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:4430:50"/>
                     <l>His ne'r-ſhak't Faith, thar <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone</l>
                     <l>(True God) our Nature hath put-on,</l>
                     <l>And Vs (markt with Deaths blackeſt Letters,</l>
                     <l>Vnto eternall Chaines and Fetters)</l>
                     <l>Hath ranſomd with his deareſt Blood,</l>
                     <l>And 'twixt God's Wrath and Vs hath ſtood:</l>
                     <l>In Heaven he ſhall ('mong <hi>Heroës</hi> bleſt)</l>
                     <l>Crownd with unblaſted Bayes ſtill reſt.</l>
                     <l>Perhaps, thou'l ſay; Theſe words are blunt;</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Romans</hi> ſo to ſpeak ar wont.</l>
                     <l>O trifling <hi>Martial,</hi> tis moſt ſure,</l>
                     <l>That theſe things a bleſt Life procure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Georg. Fabricius.</head>
                     <l>THeſe things true Happineſs doe teach,</l>
                     <l>At which well-minded Chriſtians reach:</l>
                     <l>God rightly and thy ſelfe to knowe,</l>
                     <l>And what thou doſt thy Neighbour owe;</l>
                     <l>A temperate Tongue, chaſte Speech, Heart pure,</l>
                     <l>A cheerfull Giver's Hand to th' Poore,</l>
                     <l>A Life with ſmall, and 's owne Content,</l>
                     <l>Vnſtaind Faith, and Love permanent,</l>
                     <l>A Minde with good Succeſs not drunk,</l>
                     <l>Nor with diſaſtrous chances ſhrunk,</l>
                     <l>But which good Hope keeps, and makes bolde</l>
                     <l>His Saviour <hi>Christ</hi> ſtill to beholde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ad Martialem. Lib. 5. Epigr.</hi> 21.</head>
                     <l>IF that with thee, dear <hi>Martial,</hi> I might</l>
                     <l>Securely ſpend my dayes as I deſire:</l>
                     <l>If vacant time we might diſpoſe aright,</l>
                     <l>And at the laſt to a true life retire;</l>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:4430:50"/>
                     <l>No Princes Courts, nor houſes would we knowe</l>
                     <l>Of mighty men, nor irkſome ſutes would trie,</l>
                     <l>Nor unto greedy Lawyers would we goe,</l>
                     <l>Nor poare on a proud worm-gnawn Pedegree:</l>
                     <l>But, a well-pend, and lively acted Scene,</l>
                     <l>Small Brooks, Fields, Walks, fair Damſels, Bathes and Shades,</l>
                     <l>Should be the Labours we would entertaine,</l>
                     <l>Should be the Shops wherein we ſtill would trade.</l>
                     <l>Now, neither of vs lives t' himſelfe (Alas!)</l>
                     <l>But doth perceive with grief of minde, and ſee</l>
                     <l>How fair Suns riſe, and how away they paſs</l>
                     <l>Fruit-leſs to us, for which we blamed be.</l>
                     <l>Doth not a man, to live that knowes the way,</l>
                     <l>Cut-off encumbrances that thence him ſtay?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Marcus Antonius Flaminius,</hi> ad <hi>Steph. Saulum:</hi> Sic incipiens. <hi>Ne tu beatum dixeris<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>THink not (good <hi>Saul</hi>) that hee is bleſt</l>
                     <l>Through Cities ſtately Gates that goes,</l>
                     <l>With ſwarms of crouching Suters preſt,</l>
                     <l>And noble Peers that him in cloſe.</l>
                     <l>No, not if in high-rooft Barnes he</l>
                     <l>Fair <hi>Affricks</hi> fertile Harveſts hold,</l>
                     <l>And Gems, and poliſht Ivory</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſs, and ruddy heaps of Gold.</l>
                     <l>Nor he the ſecret Seales that opes</l>
                     <l>Of Cauſes; or by skill profound</l>
                     <l>Mounts to the Stars, or by Wit gropes</l>
                     <l>To finde the Treaſures hid ith' Ground:</l>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:4430:51"/>
                     <l>But him thou Bleſſed well mayſt call.</l>
                     <l>That rightly doth his God adore,</l>
                     <l>And from his Precepts doth not fall,</l>
                     <l>But them than Gold eſteemeth more.</l>
                     <l>He's not puft-up with peoples Praiſe;</l>
                     <l>But, ſtill God's Praiſe to him is dear:</l>
                     <l>Which to maintaine and more to raiſe,</l>
                     <l>Reproches he doth willing beare.</l>
                     <l>And often, from Earth's Cares ſet free,</l>
                     <l>His happy Soule to Heaven aſcends;</l>
                     <l>Where it enioyes the Deïtie,</l>
                     <l>And parlies with celeſtiall Friends.</l>
                     <l>And ſo, full fraught with heavenly Ioy,</l>
                     <l>Vnto an higher pitch he riſeth</l>
                     <l>Than worldly Dangers can annoy,</l>
                     <l>And Mens mad purpoſes deſpiſeth.</l>
                     <l>The Shepheard ſo, from perill farre,</l>
                     <l>As he ſecure lies in his Cave,</l>
                     <l>Beholds the ſturdy Windes at warre</l>
                     <l>With Seas, that proudly ſwell and rave,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Lipſij laus, &amp; vota Vitae beatae.</head>
                     <l>HEe's like the gods, and higher then</l>
                     <l>The reſt-leſs Race of mortall Men,</l>
                     <l>That wiſheth not, or (in deſpaire)</l>
                     <l>The doubtfull Day of Death doth feare.</l>
                     <l>In whom Ambition doth not raigne,</l>
                     <l>That is not vext with hope of Gaine,</l>
                     <l>That trembles not at Threats of Kings,</l>
                     <l>Nor Darts that angry <hi>Iove</hi> down flings:</l>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:4430:51"/>
                     <l>But, firmely ſeated in one Place,</l>
                     <l>Vulgar Delights doth ſcorne, as baſe:</l>
                     <l>That of his Life one <hi>Tenor</hi> keeps;</l>
                     <l>Secure that wakes, ſecure that ſleeps.</l>
                     <l>If I might live at mine owne pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>I would no Office ſeek, nor Treaſure;</l>
                     <l>Nor captive Troups ſhould me attend,</l>
                     <l>As to my Charret I aſcend,</l>
                     <l>Drawne by white Steeds, with Shouts and Cries;</l>
                     <l>A Spectacle to gazing Eyes.</l>
                     <l>In Places I remote would be:</l>
                     <l>Gardens and Fields ſhould ſolace me:</l>
                     <l>There, at the bubbling waters noyſe,</l>
                     <l>I with the Muſes would reioyce.</l>
                     <l>So, when my <hi>Lacheſis</hi> hath ſpun</l>
                     <l>The thread of Life, ſhe well drew on;</l>
                     <l>Not unto any man a Foe,</l>
                     <l>I full of Years from hence would goe,</l>
                     <l>And Date my dayes in quiet ſtate,</l>
                     <l>As my good <hi>Langius</hi> did of late.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="metrical_Psalm">
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Pſalmus Primus</hi> DAVIDIS. <hi>Beatus vir, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <l>HEe happy is, amongſt the brain-ſick Crue</l>
                        <l>Of ill-adviſing men, that doth not walk;</l>
                        <l>Nor the lewd Path of wicked men purſue,</l>
                        <l>Of holy things that dare profanely talke;</l>
                        <l>Nor in the Scorners chaire ſits (ſwoln with Pride)</l>
                        <l>That God contemne, and Godlineſs deride.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But hee ſeeks-out farre-better Wayes to tread,</l>
                        <l>Led (in the winding Labyrinth of this Life)</l>
                        <pb n="96" facs="tcp:4430:52"/>
                        <l>By his Creator's Lawes, as a ſure thread</l>
                        <l>That guides him through croſs-wayes of worldly Strife.</l>
                        <l>By it, his Words and Actions he doth frame:</l>
                        <l>Earely and late he thinks upon the fame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Hee's like a thick-leav'd tree, that planted is</l>
                        <l>By the green Bank of ſom ſmooth-gliding Stream,</l>
                        <l>That with his fruitfull armes ſtretcht-forth doth bliſs</l>
                        <l>The Labourers Paines: which <hi>Phoebus</hi> with his beam</l>
                        <l>Doth ne'r ſo ſearch, nor Winters rage can ſtay,</l>
                        <l>But yearly Rent ſhe to her Lord will pay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>So ſhall not the ungodly and unkinde</l>
                        <l>Deſpiſers of Gods Statutes and his Grace,</l>
                        <l>That (with themſelves at war) no Reſt can finde;</l>
                        <l>But, like the Chaf, are toſt from place to place</l>
                        <l>With every ſudden blaſt of Winde that bloweth,</l>
                        <l>Which ſcorns their lightneſs, and to Heaven it ſheweth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For, when the iuſt Iudge comes in a bright Cloud,</l>
                        <l>Circled with Angels, cloath'd with Maieſty,</l>
                        <l>The wicked (daunted) will cry-out aloud,</l>
                        <l>Casſhierd from Saints for their impiety.</l>
                        <l>For, as in good mens Wayes God takes Delight,</l>
                        <l>So he o'r-throwes all wicked By-wayes quite.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4430:52"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
